BC	O
-	O
PEARL-HARBOR	LOCATION
-	O
HNS	O
&LR;	O
01-02	DATE
BC	O
-	O
PEARL-HARBOR	LOCATION
-	O
HNS	O
PENTAGON	ORGANIZATION
BLOCKS	O
MOVE	O
TO	O
PROMOTE	O
PEARL	LOCATION
HARBOR	LOCATION
COMMANDERS	O
-LRB-	O
For	O
use	O
by	O
New	ORGANIZATION
York	ORGANIZATION
Times	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
clients	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
By	O
CHARLES	PERSON
J.	PERSON
LEWIS	PERSON
c.	O
1996	DATE
Hearst	ORGANIZATION
Newspapers	ORGANIZATION
WASHINGTON	LOCATION
--	O
The	O
Pentagon	ORGANIZATION
has	O
denied	O
a	O
request	O
that	O
top	O
U.S.	LOCATION
commanders	O
in	O
Hawaii	LOCATION
in	O
1941	DATE
be	O
absolved	O
of	O
blame	O
for	O
failing	O
to	O
be	O
on	O
alert	O
for	O
the	O
Japanese	O
attack	O
on	O
Pearl	LOCATION
Harbor	LOCATION
,	O
but	O
the	O
military	O
agreed	O
that	O
top	O
Washington	LOCATION
officials	O
also	O
must	O
share	O
the	O
blame	O
.	O
A	O
Pentagon	ORGANIZATION
study	O
re-affirmed	O
the	O
conclusion	O
of	O
previous	O
government	O
investigations	O
that	O
both	O
Rear	O
Admiral	O
Husband	PERSON
E.	PERSON
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
his	O
Army	ORGANIZATION
counterpart	O
,	O
Maj.	O
Gen.	O
Walter	PERSON
C.	PERSON
Short	PERSON
,	O
``	O
committed	O
errors	O
of	O
judgment	O
''	O
leading	O
up	O
to	O
the	O
Dec.	DATE
7	DATE
,	DATE
1941	DATE
,	O
debacle	O
.	O
However	O
,	O
the	O
Pentagon	ORGANIZATION
study	O
made	O
a	O
bow	O
in	O
the	O
direction	O
of	O
Kimmel	PERSON
's	O
and	O
Short	PERSON
's	O
advocates	O
by	O
criticizing	O
top	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
and	O
Army	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
in	O
Washington	LOCATION
for	O
being	O
``	O
neither	O
energetic	O
nor	O
effective	O
in	O
getting	O
''	O
warnings	O
to	O
Hawaii	LOCATION
about	O
alarming	O
intelligence	O
reports	O
that	O
a	O
U.S.	LOCATION
-	O
Japanese	O
rupture	O
was	O
just	O
hours	O
away	O
.	O
Washington	LOCATION
also	O
failed	O
to	O
give	O
Pearl	LOCATION
Harbor	LOCATION
a	O
heads-up	O
that	O
the	O
Japanese	O
consulate	O
in	O
Honolulu	LOCATION
was	O
tracking	O
the	O
precise	O
location	O
of	O
U.S.	LOCATION
ships	O
moored	O
in	O
Pearl	LOCATION
Harbor	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
handling	O
of	O
these	O
warnings	O
``	O
reveals	O
some	O
ineptitude	O
,	O
some	O
unwarranted	O
assumptions	O
and	O
misestimates	O
,	O
limited	O
coordination	O
,	O
ambiguous	O
language	O
and	O
lack	O
of	O
clarification	O
and	O
follow-up	O
at	O
higher	O
levels	O
,	O
''	O
according	O
to	O
the	O
report	O
by	O
Edwin	PERSON
Dorn	PERSON
,	O
under	O
secretary	O
of	O
defense	ORGANIZATION
for	O
personnel	O
and	O
readiness	O
.	O
However	O
,	O
``	O
to	O
say	O
that	O
responsibility	O
is	O
broadly	O
shared	O
is	O
not	O
to	O
absolve	O
Admiral	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
General	O
Short	PERSON
of	O
accountability	O
,	O
''	O
the	O
Dorn	O
report	O
said	O
.	O
The	O
seven-month	O
re-examination	O
of	O
why	O
U.S.	LOCATION
forces	O
were	O
caught	O
off-guard	O
by	O
the	O
Japanese	O
attack	O
was	O
done	O
at	O
the	O
request	O
of	O
Sen.	O
Strom	PERSON
Thurmond	PERSON
,	O
R	O
-	O
S.C.	LOCATION
,	O
chairman	O
of	O
the	O
Senate	ORGANIZATION
Armed	ORGANIZATION
Services	ORGANIZATION
Committee	ORGANIZATION
,	O
and	O
members	O
of	O
the	O
Kimmel	PERSON
family	O
.	O
In	O
the	O
midst	O
of	O
last	DATE
year	DATE
's	O
commemorations	O
of	O
the	O
50th	DATE
anniversary	DATE
of	DATE
the	DATE
end	DATE
of	DATE
World	DATE
War	DATE
II	DATE
,	O
the	O
Kimmel	PERSON
family	O
asked	O
the	O
Pentagon	ORGANIZATION
to	O
restore	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
to	O
their	O
highest	O
ranks	O
posthumously	O
as	O
symbolic	O
recognition	O
that	O
they	O
had	O
been	O
made	O
scapegoats	O
for	O
the	O
mistakes	O
of	O
others	O
.	O
Kimmel	PERSON
held	O
four-star	O
rank	O
and	O
Short	PERSON
wore	O
three	O
stars	O
on	O
the	O
day	O
of	O
the	O
attack	O
.	O
Within	O
two	O
weeks	O
of	O
the	O
attack	O
,	O
both	O
men	O
were	O
relieved	O
of	O
their	O
commands	O
and	O
automatically	O
demoted	O
to	O
two-star	O
rank	O
.	O
They	O
retired	O
from	O
active	O
duty	O
early	DATE
in	DATE
1942	DATE
.	O
Edward	PERSON
R.	PERSON
Kimmel	PERSON
,	O
one	O
of	O
Admiral	O
Kimmel	PERSON
's	O
two	O
surviving	O
sons	O
and	O
a	O
leader	O
of	O
the	O
campaign	O
to	O
exonerate	O
his	O
father	O
,	O
said	O
the	O
Dorn	O
report	O
confirms	O
the	O
assertions	O
of	O
the	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
families	O
that	O
the	O
responsibility	O
should	O
be	O
broadly	O
shared	O
and	O
not	O
placed	O
on	O
the	O
shoulders	O
of	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
exclusively	O
.	O
``	O
This	O
is	O
very	O
affirmative	O
from	O
the	O
standpoint	O
of	O
the	O
Kimmel	PERSON
family	O
,	O
''	O
he	O
said	O
.	O
``	O
Dorn	PERSON
did	O
a	O
fine	O
job	O
.	O
''	O
Thurmond	PERSON
expressed	O
regret	O
that	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
were	O
n't	O
restored	O
to	O
their	O
higher	O
ranks	O
but	O
expressed	O
confidence	O
that	O
further	O
historical	O
study	O
will	O
restore	O
the	O
``	O
good	O
names	O
of	O
these	O
two	O
men	O
.	O
''	O
Dorn	PERSON
's	O
conclusion	O
that	O
Washington	LOCATION
also	O
should	O
share	O
the	O
blame	O
for	O
Pearl	LOCATION
Harbor	LOCATION
is	O
in	O
line	O
with	O
recent	O
historical	O
scholarship	O
showing	O
mind-boggling	O
incompetence	O
,	O
power-plays	O
,	O
harmful	O
rivalries	O
and	O
clumsy	O
communications	O
among	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
and	O
Army	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
in	O
Washington	LOCATION
.	O
In	O
addition	O
to	O
the	O
bungled	O
handling	O
of	O
intelligence	O
reports	O
,	O
Washington	LOCATION
officials	O
come	O
under	O
criticism	O
in	O
the	O
Dorn	O
report	O
in	O
other	O
areas	O
.	O
Dorn	PERSON
notes	O
that	O
the	O
get-tough	O
policy	O
of	O
the	O
Franklin	PERSON
D.	PERSON
Roosevelt	PERSON
administration	O
toward	O
Japan	LOCATION
--	O
designed	O
to	O
persuade	O
Japan	LOCATION
to	O
rein	O
in	O
its	O
military	O
expansionism	O
in	O
China	LOCATION
and	O
Southeast	LOCATION
Asia	LOCATION
--	O
included	O
an	O
embargo	O
against	O
oil	O
exports	O
to	O
Japan	LOCATION
and	O
the	O
freezing	O
of	O
Japanese	O
assets	O
in	O
the	O
summer	DATE
of	DATE
1941	DATE
.	O
The	O
report	O
suggests	O
that	O
FDR	PERSON
backed	O
Japan	LOCATION
into	O
a	O
corner	O
.	O
Dorn	PERSON
also	O
cites	O
the	O
``	O
muddied	O
''	O
warnings	O
that	O
Washington	LOCATION
sent	O
10	O
days	O
before	O
the	O
attack	O
to	O
Pearl	LOCATION
Harbor	LOCATION
about	O
the	O
imminence	O
of	O
war	O
and	O
Washington	LOCATION
's	O
failure	O
to	O
follow	O
up	O
its	O
warnings	O
to	O
check	O
to	O
see	O
what	O
the	O
Hawaii	LOCATION
commanders	O
were	O
doing	O
to	O
prepare	O
.	O
The	O
Dorn	O
report	O
noted	O
that	O
previous	O
congressional	O
,	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
and	O
Army	ORGANIZATION
investigations	O
had	O
also	O
``	O
properly	O
recognized	O
and	O
criticized	O
''	O
the	O
failures	O
of	O
senior	O
Washington	LOCATION
military	O
leaders	O
.	O
On	O
the	O
other	O
side	O
of	O
the	O
ledger	O
,	O
the	O
Dorn	O
report	O
says	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
had	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
intelligence	O
that	O
``	O
was	O
sufficient	O
to	O
justify	O
a	O
higher	O
level	O
of	O
vigilance	O
than	O
they	O
chose	O
to	O
maintain	O
.	O
''	O
For	O
example	O
,	O
Dorn	PERSON
said	O
,	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
knew	O
that	O
war	O
with	O
Japan	LOCATION
was	O
``	O
highly	O
likely	O
''	O
and	O
that	O
Japan	LOCATION
would	O
strike	O
the	O
first	O
blow	O
.	O
And	O
they	O
knew	O
that	O
the	O
attack	O
``	O
could	O
occur	O
within	O
weeks	O
or	O
days	O
''	O
because	O
tension	O
between	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
and	O
Japan	LOCATION
had	O
been	O
building	O
.	O
Both	O
commanders	O
had	O
received	O
a	O
``	O
war	O
warning	O
''	O
from	O
Washington	LOCATION
in	O
late	DATE
November	DATE
to	O
be	O
on	O
the	O
alert	O
against	O
a	O
possible	O
attack	O
.	O
Both	O
commanders	O
also	O
knew	O
the	O
Japanese	O
liked	O
to	O
spring	O
surprise	O
attacks	O
,	O
especially	O
on	O
weekends	O
.	O
Kimmel	PERSON
also	O
knew	O
that	O
his	O
intelligence	O
staff	O
had	O
suddenly	O
lost	O
track	O
of	O
Japan	LOCATION
's	O
aircraft	O
carriers	O
and	O
that	O
Japanese	O
embassies	O
and	O
consulates	O
had	O
been	O
ordered	O
to	O
destroy	O
their	O
secret	O
codes	O
.	O
The	O
report	O
also	O
notes	O
the	O
confused	O
assumptions	O
that	O
governed	O
the	O
relationship	O
between	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
.	O
For	O
example	O
,	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
had	O
responsibility	O
for	O
long-range	O
defensive	O
patrols	O
around	O
Pearl	LOCATION
Harbor	LOCATION
,	O
but	O
Short	PERSON
apparently	O
never	O
asked	O
Kimmel	PERSON
exactly	O
what	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
was	O
doing	O
in	O
that	O
respect	O
.	O
This	O
was	O
a	O
key	O
mistake	O
in	O
view	O
of	O
the	O
fact	O
that	O
Short	PERSON
's	O
fighter	O
planes	O
needed	O
a	O
four-hour	O
warning	O
before	O
they	O
could	O
get	O
in	O
the	O
air	O
and	O
do	O
battle	O
.	O
In	O
reality	O
,	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
was	O
undertaking	O
only	O
minimal	O
reconnaissance	O
,	O
mainly	O
because	O
of	O
a	O
lack	O
of	O
airplanes	O
.	O
Nonetheless	O
,	O
the	O
Hawaii	LOCATION
commanders	O
did	O
n't	O
know	O
when	O
or	O
where	O
the	O
attack	O
would	O
come	O
.	O
Dorn	PERSON
said	O
higher	O
alert	O
by	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
``	O
might	O
not	O
have	O
discovered	O
the	O
-LRB-	O
Japanese	O
-RRB-	O
carrier	O
armada	O
and	O
might	O
not	O
have	O
prevented	O
the	O
attack	O
,	O
but	O
different	O
choices	O
...	O
could	O
have	O
reduced	O
the	O
magnitude	O
of	O
the	O
disaster	O
.	O
''	O
The	O
attack	O
killed	O
2,403	O
Americans	O
and	O
sank	O
or	O
damaged	O
18	O
warships	O
.	O
The	O
bottom	O
line	O
:	O
There	O
's	O
no	O
basis	O
to	O
restore	O
their	O
higher	O
rank	O
.	O
Besides	O
,	O
Dorn	PERSON
noted	O
,	O
``	O
Retirement	O
at	O
the	O
two-star	O
grade	O
is	O
not	O
an	O
insult	O
or	O
a	O
stigma	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
Dorn	PERSON
's	O
decision	O
was	O
praised	O
by	O
both	O
sides	O
of	O
the	O
historical	O
debate	O
over	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
.	O
Edward	PERSON
L.	PERSON
Beach	PERSON
,	O
a	O
retired	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
captain	O
and	O
author	O
of	O
a	O
1994	DATE
book	O
defending	O
Kimmel	PERSON
and	O
Short	PERSON
,	O
praised	O
the	O
Dorn	O
report	O
for	O
``	O
restoring	O
their	O
honor	O
without	O
promoting	O
them	O
by	O
acknowledging	O
that	O
others	O
also	O
were	O
guilty	O
.	O
This	O
paper	O
removes	O
the	O
stigma	O
in	O
the	O
court	O
of	O
public	O
opinion	O
.	O
''	O
Donald	PERSON
M.	PERSON
Goldstein	PERSON
,	O
a	O
historian	O
at	O
the	O
University	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Pittsburgh	ORGANIZATION
who	O
helped	O
write	O
the	O
best-selling	O
Pearl	LOCATION
Harbor	LOCATION
history	O
``	O
At	O
Dawn	O
We	O
Slept	O
,	O
''	O
also	O
lauded	O
the	O
report	O
.	O
``	O
Given	O
all	O
that	O
we	O
've	O
seen	O
,	O
we	O
know	O
it	O
was	O
on	O
their	O
watch	O
.	O
To	O
exonerate	O
them	O
,	O
you	O
'd	O
have	O
to	O
go	O
back	O
and	O
exonerate	O
everybody	O
who	O
screwed	O
up	O
at	O
Pearl	LOCATION
Harbor	LOCATION
.	O
If	O
they	O
had	O
caught	O
the	O
Japanese	O
,	O
they	O
would	O
have	O
been	O
heroes	O
.	O
But	O
they	O
did	O
n't	O
.	O
And	O
they	O
were	O
out	O
there	O
to	O
defend	O
the	O
place	O
and	O
they	O
should	O
have	O
been	O
ready	O
.	O
''	O
NYT	O
-	O
01-02-96	DATE
1907EST	TIME

BC	O
-	O
LOGAN	LOCATION
-	O
RUNWAYS-BOS	O
&LR;	O
01-12	DATE
BC	O
-	O
LOGAN	LOCATION
-	O
RUNWAYS-BOS	O
PILOTS	O
SAY	O
LOGAN	LOCATION
RUNWAYS	O
HAZARDOUS	O
-LRB-	O
For	O
use	O
by	O
New	ORGANIZATION
York	ORGANIZATION
Times	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
clients	O
-RRB-	O
By	O
MATTHEW	PERSON
BRELIS	PERSON
c.	O
1996	DATE
The	ORGANIZATION
Boston	ORGANIZATION
Globe	ORGANIZATION
BOSTON	LOCATION
--	O
Pilots	O
flying	O
in	O
and	O
out	O
of	O
Logan	LOCATION
International	LOCATION
Airport	LOCATION
have	O
become	O
so	O
concerned	O
about	O
safety	O
hazards	O
like	O
snow-slick	O
runways	O
and	O
taxiway	O
signs	O
obscured	O
by	O
drifts	O
that	O
they	O
have	O
complained	O
to	O
their	O
airlines	O
and	O
circulated	O
a	O
pilots	O
'	O
petition	O
blasting	O
Massport	ORGANIZATION
as	O
``	O
inept	O
.	O
''	O
``	O
Pilots	O
of	O
several	O
major	O
carriers	O
are	O
concerned	O
about	O
the	O
lack	O
of	O
markings	O
and	O
the	O
condition	O
of	O
runways	O
and	O
taxiways	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
Paul	PERSON
McCarthy	PERSON
,	O
chairman	O
of	O
the	O
accident	O
investigation	O
board	O
for	O
the	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
Line	ORGANIZATION
Pilots	ORGANIZATION
Association	ORGANIZATION
.	O
McCarthy	PERSON
said	O
he	O
been	O
told	O
of	O
the	O
pilots	O
'	O
concerns	O
by	O
air	O
safety	O
officials	O
from	O
at	O
least	O
three	O
major	O
airlines	O
.	O
Meanwhile	O
,	O
a	O
separate	O
group	O
of	O
pilots	O
has	O
drafted	O
a	O
strongly	O
worded	O
petition	O
complaining	O
to	O
US	ORGANIZATION
Transportation	ORGANIZATION
Secretary	O
Federico	PERSON
Pena	PERSON
about	O
the	O
conditions	O
.	O
``	O
From	O
our	O
experience	O
,	O
it	O
is	O
obvious	O
that	O
Massport	ORGANIZATION
is	O
an	O
inept	O
organization	O
incapable	O
of	O
handling	O
daily	O
operations	O
in	O
a	O
manner	O
that	O
provides	O
safety	O
comparable	O
to	O
other	O
major	O
airports	O
in	O
the	O
Northeast	O
,	O
''	O
reads	O
the	O
petition	O
,	O
a	O
copy	O
of	O
which	O
was	O
obtained	O
by	O
the	ORGANIZATION
Globe	ORGANIZATION
.	O
``	O
While	O
other	O
major	O
airports	O
have	O
effectively	O
removed	O
snow	O
from	O
their	O
surfaces	O
,	O
Massport	ORGANIZATION
's	O
inability	O
to	O
plow	O
runways	O
and	O
taxiways	O
properly	O
and	O
in	O
a	O
timely	O
manner	O
leaves	O
Logan	LOCATION
Airport	LOCATION
an	O
unnecessary	O
disaster	O
weeks	O
after	O
a	O
snowstorm	O
.	O
``	O
This	O
poor	O
operation	O
places	O
aircraft	O
,	O
ground	O
equipment	O
and	O
personnel	O
in	O
extremely	O
hazardous	O
conditions	O
which	O
compromise	O
the	O
high	O
level	O
of	O
safety	O
which	O
the	O
airline	O
industry	O
constantly	O
strives	O
to	O
achieve	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
the	O
petition	O
,	O
which	O
sources	O
said	O
has	O
yet	O
to	O
be	O
sent	O
to	O
Pena	PERSON
.	O
Massport	ORGANIZATION
,	O
which	O
owns	O
and	O
operates	O
Logan	LOCATION
,	O
defended	O
the	O
attempts	O
to	O
remove	O
snow	O
,	O
saying	O
crews	O
are	O
doing	O
their	O
best	O
to	O
keep	O
the	O
airport	O
open	O
while	O
maintaining	O
safety	O
.	O
``	O
The	O
conditions	O
speak	O
for	O
themselves	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
Thomas	PERSON
Kinton	PERSON
,	O
director	O
of	O
aviation	O
.	O
``	O
If	O
a	O
pilot	O
,	O
prior	O
to	O
departure	O
,	O
wants	O
to	O
view	O
the	O
runway	O
firsthand	O
,	O
he	O
can	O
.	O
And	O
there	O
has	O
not	O
been	O
one	O
incident	O
where	O
a	O
pilot	O
refused	O
to	O
take	O
the	O
runway	O
.	O
''	O
A	O
regularly	O
updated	O
tape	O
recording	O
of	O
field	O
conditions	O
makes	O
incoming	O
and	O
outgoing	O
pilots	O
aware	O
of	O
what	O
signs	O
are	O
broken	O
or	O
obscured	O
by	O
snow	O
.	O
Of	O
the	O
50	O
mandatory	O
signs	O
at	O
Logan	LOCATION
,	O
12	O
were	O
not	O
working	O
Friday	DATE
.	O
``	O
Are	O
these	O
conditions	O
great	O
?	O
''	O
asked	O
Kinton	PERSON
.	O
``	O
Hell	O
,	O
no	O
.	O
But	O
the	O
snow	O
we	O
've	O
had	O
is	O
unprecedented	O
.	O
''	O
Kinton	PERSON
said	O
he	O
will	O
meet	O
with	O
chief	O
pilots	O
of	O
the	O
airlines	O
next	DATE
week	DATE
and	O
ask	O
if	O
they	O
want	O
Logan	LOCATION
to	O
close	O
for	O
longer	O
periods	O
of	O
time	O
for	O
snow	O
removal	O
.	O
``	O
Our	O
objective	O
has	O
been	O
to	O
keep	O
the	O
airport	O
open	O
.	O
We	O
do	O
quick	O
plows	O
on	O
the	O
runways	O
and	O
as	O
a	O
result	O
,	O
taxiways	O
get	O
hard-packed	O
before	O
we	O
can	O
remove	O
the	O
snow	O
.	O
''	O
But	O
veteran	O
pilots	O
who	O
are	O
based	O
in	O
Boston	LOCATION
say	O
more	O
than	O
taxiway	O
conditions	O
are	O
deplorable	O
.	O
``	O
Finding	O
your	O
way	O
around	O
Logan	LOCATION
at	O
night	O
is	O
an	O
adventure	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
one	O
pilot	O
who	O
spoke	O
on	O
condition	O
neither	O
his	O
name	O
or	O
airline	O
be	O
disclosed	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
flew	O
in	O
there	O
-LRB-	O
Thursday	DATE
-RRB-	O
night	TIME
and	O
we	O
were	O
laughing	O
out	O
loud	O
in	O
the	O
cockpit	O
at	O
some	O
of	O
the	O
sights	O
.	O
''	O
Plows	O
had	O
buried	O
illuminated	O
taxiway	O
signs	O
,	O
making	O
it	O
difficult	O
for	O
pilots	O
unfamiliar	O
with	O
the	O
airport	O
to	O
follow	O
air	O
traffic	O
control	O
instructions	O
.	O
With	O
signs	O
obscured	O
,	O
pilots	O
have	O
a	O
hard	O
time	O
knowing	O
where	O
to	O
hold	O
short	O
of	O
runways	O
,	O
increasing	O
the	O
chance	O
of	O
two	O
planes	O
colliding	O
on	O
the	O
ground	O
.	O
``	O
We	O
're	O
concerned	O
about	O
runway	O
incursions	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
one	O
aviation	O
safety	O
offical	O
.	O
``	O
The	O
boundaries	O
between	O
runways	O
and	O
taxiways	O
are	O
obscured	O
.	O
''	O
Kinton	PERSON
said	O
there	O
had	O
been	O
no	O
runway	O
incursions	O
.	O
``	O
There	O
have	O
been	O
a	O
couple	O
of	O
incidents	O
where	O
aircraft	O
got	O
stuck	O
,	O
''	O
he	O
said	O
.	O
In	O
the	O
last	DATE
three	DATE
days	DATE
,	O
at	O
least	O
three	O
planes	O
have	O
become	O
disabled	O
at	O
Logan	LOCATION
in	O
incidents	O
pilots	O
attribute	O
directly	O
to	O
the	O
weather	O
.	O
On	O
Thursday	DATE
evening	TIME
a	O
Continental	ORGANIZATION
Airlines	ORGANIZATION
jet	O
from	O
Newark	LOCATION
,	O
went	O
into	O
a	O
snowbank	O
after	O
turning	O
on	O
to	O
a	O
hard-packed	O
taxiway	O
.	O
A	O
Continental	ORGANIZATION
spokesman	O
said	O
the	O
plane	O
was	O
moving	O
at	O
7	O
miles	O
per	O
hour	O
when	O
the	O
nose	O
wheel	O
lost	O
traction	O
,	O
causing	O
the	O
plane	O
to	O
run	O
wide	O
.	O
The	O
left	O
landing	O
gear	O
went	O
into	O
an	O
unplowed	O
area	O
of	O
the	O
taxiway	O
.	O
On	O
Wednesday	DATE
,	O
an	O
American	ORGANIZATION
Airlines	ORGANIZATION
flight	O
slid	O
into	O
snow	O
when	O
the	O
jet	O
blast	O
of	O
a	O
departing	O
aircraft	O
pushed	O
the	O
nose	O
wheel	O
,	O
and	O
a	O
Business	ORGANIZATION
Express	ORGANIZATION
aircraft	O
that	O
had	O
turned	O
on	O
to	O
a	O
closed	O
,	O
unplowed	O
taxiway	O
had	O
to	O
be	O
pulled	O
from	O
a	O
snowbank	O
.	O
``	O
These	O
are	O
very	O
minor	O
incidents	O
and	O
are	O
not	O
alarming	O
to	O
me	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
Kinton	PERSON
.	O
``	O
Things	O
happen	O
when	O
you	O
have	O
conditions	O
that	O
are	O
less	O
than	O
optimal	O
.	O
''	O
Pilots	O
say	O
other	O
major	O
northeast	O
airports	O
near	O
water	O
,	O
such	O
as	O
LaGuardia	LOCATION
,	O
Newark	LOCATION
and	O
Philadelphia	LOCATION
,	O
have	O
runways	O
and	O
taxiways	O
that	O
are	O
bare	O
and	O
dry	O
,	O
while	O
Logan	LOCATION
's	O
have	O
hard-packed	O
snow	O
.	O
Kinton	PERSON
said	O
those	O
airports	O
&UR;	O
&LR;	O
have	O
had	O
less	O
snow	O
this	DATE
winter	DATE
than	O
Boston	LOCATION
.	O
It	O
was	O
not	O
until	O
Friday	DATE
afternoon	TIME
that	O
snow	O
was	O
removed	O
from	O
around	O
antenna	O
arrays	O
at	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
Logan	LOCATION
's	O
runways	O
making	O
the	O
instrument	O
landing	O
systems	O
operational	O
,	O
said	O
Federal	ORGANIZATION
Aviation	ORGANIZATION
Administration	ORGANIZATION
spokeswoman	O
Mary	PERSON
Culver	PERSON
.	O
Without	O
the	O
landing	O
systems	O
,	O
pilots	O
used	O
non-precision	O
approaches	O
which	O
resulted	O
in	O
delays	O
because	O
planes	O
were	O
spaced	O
further	O
apart	O
,	O
she	O
said	O
.	O
-LRB-	O
Andrew	PERSON
Blake	PERSON
of	O
the	ORGANIZATION
Globe	ORGANIZATION
Staff	ORGANIZATION
contributed	O
to	O
this	O
report	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
NYT	O
-	O
01-12-96	DATE
2302EST	TIME

BC-CHALLENGER-FAMILIES-2	O
01-26	DATE
0935	O
BC-CHALLENGER-FAMILIES-2NDTAKE	O
-	O
$	O
ADV28-HNS	O
FRAMINGHAM	LOCATION
,	O
Mass.	LOCATION
:	O
at	O
face	O
value	O
.	O
``	O
He	O
said	O
,	O
`	O
They	O
showed	O
us	O
a	O
picture	O
of	O
it	O
launching	O
in	O
the	O
snow	O
,	O
''	O
'	O
Rogers	PERSON
recalled	O
.	O
``	O
`	O
They	O
said	O
it	O
would	O
be	O
OK	O
.	O
'	O
``	O
I	O
'm	O
so	O
much	O
smarter	O
now	O
,	O
''	O
she	O
said	O
.	O
``	O
Now	O
I	O
would	O
have	O
said	O
,	O
`	O
Are	O
you	O
talking	O
about	O
administration	O
?	O
Are	O
you	O
talking	O
about	O
engineers	O
?	O
''	O
'	O
The	O
Scobee	PERSON
children	O
were	O
in	O
their	O
early	O
20s	O
at	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
the	O
Challenger	O
disaster	O
.	O
Kathie	PERSON
Scobee	PERSON
Fulgham	PERSON
is	O
a	O
public	O
relations	O
director	O
in	O
Houston	LOCATION
.	O
and	O
Rich	PERSON
Scobee	PERSON
is	O
an	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
Force	ORGANIZATION
pilot	O
who	O
served	O
in	O
Desert	O
Storm	O
and	O
whose	O
risk-taking	O
profession	O
probably	O
rivals	O
that	O
of	O
this	O
father	O
.	O
``	O
Dick	PERSON
Scobee	PERSON
flew	O
as	O
a	O
test	O
pilot	O
,	O
''	O
Rogers	PERSON
said	O
,	O
mulling	O
the	O
similarities	O
between	O
father	O
and	O
son	O
.	O
``	O
Some	O
of	O
those	O
test	O
flights	O
were	O
more	O
dangerous	O
,	O
I	O
thought	O
,	O
than	O
the	O
space	O
shuttle	O
.	O
''	O
&UR;	O
--	O
&LR;	O
The	O
memorial	O
service	O
for	O
the	O
Challenger	O
crew	O
was	O
held	O
three	O
days	O
after	O
the	O
accident	O
.	O
It	O
was	O
an	O
outdoor	O
ceremony	O
with	O
President	O
and	O
Mrs.	O
Reagan	PERSON
and	O
the	O
numbed	O
families	O
of	O
the	O
crew	O
sitting	O
under	O
a	O
cloudy	O
sky	O
at	O
the	O
Johnson	ORGANIZATION
Space	ORGANIZATION
Center	ORGANIZATION
in	O
Houston	LOCATION
.	O
Toward	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
the	O
service	O
,	O
a	O
squadron	O
of	O
jets	O
screamed	O
across	O
the	O
sky	O
in	O
the	O
``	O
missing	O
man	O
formation	O
,	O
''	O
prompting	O
the	O
widow	O
of	O
Pilot	O
Mike	PERSON
Smith	PERSON
to	O
look	O
up	O
and	O
smile	O
.	O
Jane	PERSON
Smith	PERSON
Wolcott	PERSON
still	O
reacts	O
that	O
way	O
to	O
the	O
sight	O
and	O
sound	O
of	O
airplanes	O
.	O
She	O
married	O
Norfolk	LOCATION
,	O
Va.	LOCATION
,	O
physician	O
Dixon	PERSON
Wolcott	PERSON
,	O
a	O
longtime	O
family	O
friend	O
,	O
after	O
Mike	PERSON
Smith	PERSON
's	O
death	O
and	O
clearly	O
enjoys	O
her	O
new	O
home	O
's	O
proximity	O
to	O
a	O
naval	O
air	O
base	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
'm	O
so	O
proud	O
of	O
those	O
people	O
who	O
fly	O
,	O
''	O
Wolcott	PERSON
said	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
love	O
airplanes	O
.	O
My	O
back	O
yard	O
faces	O
in	O
the	O
direction	O
of	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
bases	O
.	O
I	O
never	O
get	O
tired	O
of	O
the	O
sound	O
of	O
an	O
airplane	O
.	O
``	O
When	O
I	O
see	O
a	O
plane	O
,	O
I	O
think	O
of	O
Mike	PERSON
.	O
''	O
She	O
still	O
misses	O
him	O
terribly	O
,	O
she	O
admits	O
.	O
``	O
He	O
was	O
a	O
very	O
vital	O
man	O
,	O
with	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
energy	O
,	O
goals	O
and	O
a	O
great	O
deal	O
of	O
humility	O
,	O
''	O
Wolcott	PERSON
said	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
would	O
just	O
love	O
to	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
talk	O
with	O
him	O
.	O
''	O
And	O
every	O
Jan.	DATE
28	DATE
is	O
the	O
same	O
,	O
she	O
says	O
--	O
simply	O
awful	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
always	O
remember	O
it	O
.	O
I	O
will	O
never	O
forget	O
it	O
,	O
''	O
Wolcott	PERSON
said	O
.	O
The	O
three	O
Smith	PERSON
children	O
were	O
8	O
,	O
14	O
and	O
17	O
when	O
they	O
lost	O
their	O
father	O
.	O
Wolcott	PERSON
said	O
it	O
was	O
especially	O
hard	O
for	O
Erin	PERSON
,	O
the	O
widely	O
photographed	O
little	O
trouper	O
who	O
brought	O
strangers	O
to	O
tears	O
when	O
she	O
arrived	O
at	O
the	O
Houston	LOCATION
memorial	O
service	O
clutching	O
a	O
teddy	O
bear	O
.	O
Erin	PERSON
is	O
now	O
18	O
and	O
starting	O
college	O
.	O
Allison	PERSON
,	O
24	O
,	O
is	O
married	O
and	O
teaching	O
fourth	O
grade	O
in	O
Houston	LOCATION
.	O
Scott	PERSON
,	O
27	O
,	O
is	O
married	O
and	O
lives	O
in	O
Boston	LOCATION
.	O
&UR;	O
--	O
&LR;	O
The	O
families	O
of	O
Mission	O
Specialists	O
Ron	PERSON
McNair	PERSON
and	O
Ellison	PERSON
Onizuka	PERSON
still	O
live	O
in	O
Houston	LOCATION
.	O
McNair	PERSON
's	O
children	O
were	O
the	O
youngest	O
of	O
the	O
crew	O
's	O
offspring	O
at	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
the	O
accident	O
.	O
Joy	PERSON
is	O
now	O
11	O
.	O
Reggie	PERSON
is	O
13	O
and	O
obsessed	O
with	O
basketball	O
,	O
according	O
to	O
his	O
mother	O
.	O
Cheryl	PERSON
McNair	PERSON
confesses	O
she	O
is	O
surprised	O
by	O
the	O
level	O
of	O
concern	O
people	O
still	O
express	O
for	O
her	O
family	O
10	O
years	O
after	O
the	O
accident	O
.	O
In	O
her	O
work	O
with	O
the	O
Challenger	ORGANIZATION
Center	ORGANIZATION
and	O
with	O
a	O
Houston	LOCATION
foundation	O
,	O
strangers	O
go	O
out	O
of	O
their	O
way	O
to	O
tell	O
her	O
how	O
affected	O
they	O
were	O
by	O
the	O
death	O
of	O
the	O
crew	O
.	O
Her	O
children	O
do	O
n't	O
really	O
remember	O
their	O
father	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
mercifully	O
do	O
n't	O
remember	O
being	O
at	O
Cape	LOCATION
Canaveral	LOCATION
,	O
Fla.	LOCATION
,	O
the	O
day	O
he	O
died	O
.	O
But	O
their	O
mother	O
is	O
convinced	O
his	O
life	O
continues	O
to	O
make	O
an	O
impact	O
on	O
them	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
caught	O
Reggie	PERSON
when	O
he	O
was	O
much	O
younger	O
counting	O
his	O
dad	O
's	O
trophies	O
,	O
''	O
McNair	PERSON
said	O
.	O
``	O
And	O
I	O
said	O
,	O
`	O
Well	O
,	O
hey	O
,	O
what	O
are	O
you	O
doing	O
?	O
'	O
And	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
counting	O
those	O
trophies	O
,	O
because	O
he	O
was	O
going	O
to	O
get	O
as	O
many	O
as	O
his	O
dad	O
.	O
``	O
Ron	PERSON
did	O
so	O
much	O
in	O
the	O
short	O
amount	O
of	O
time	O
he	O
was	O
here	O
,	O
''	O
McNair	PERSON
said	O
.	O
``	O
He	O
was	O
just	O
excited	O
about	O
everything	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
always	O
thought	O
he	O
would	O
do	O
something	O
extraordinary	O
with	O
his	O
life	O
,	O
because	O
he	O
was	O
that	O
kind	O
of	O
person	O
.	O
''	O
&UR;	O
--	O
&LR;	O
Payload	O
specialist	O
Gregory	PERSON
Jarvis	PERSON
'	O
widow	O
,	O
Marcia	PERSON
Jarvis	PERSON
,	O
lives	O
in	O
Mammoth	LOCATION
Lakes	LOCATION
,	O
Calif.	LOCATION
,	O
and	O
is	O
on	O
the	O
national	O
Challenger	ORGANIZATION
Center	ORGANIZATION
board	O
.	O
She	O
likes	O
her	O
privacy	O
and	O
reportedly	O
works	O
at	O
a	O
local	O
ski	O
resort	O
.	O
She	O
has	O
not	O
remarried	O
.	O
Jarvis	PERSON
'	O
father	O
and	O
stepmother	O
live	O
about	O
45	O
miles	O
outside	O
Cape	LOCATION
Canaveral	LOCATION
,	O
where	O
nearly	O
every	O
NASA	ORGANIZATION
rocket	O
is	O
launched	O
.	O
But	O
Bruce	PERSON
Jarvis	PERSON
studiously	O
avoids	O
each	O
launch	O
,	O
not	O
because	O
of	O
the	O
memory	O
it	O
conjures	O
of	O
that	DATE
day	DATE
10	DATE
years	DATE
ago	DATE
,	O
but	O
because	O
he	O
thinks	O
his	O
presence	O
is	O
bad	O
luck	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
do	O
n't	O
watch	O
them	O
at	O
all	O
,	O
''	O
he	O
said	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
wo	O
n't	O
go	O
over	O
there	O
.	O
''	O
He	O
watched	O
two	O
of	O
NASA	ORGANIZATION
's	O
early	O
launches	O
back	O
in	O
the	O
days	O
of	O
the	O
unmanned	O
Delta	O
rockets	O
,	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
and	O
they	O
both	O
exploded	O
.	O
He	O
had	O
n't	O
seen	O
another	O
launch	O
until	O
Challenger	O
.	O
Maybe	O
common	O
sense	O
tells	O
Jarvis	PERSON
he	O
is	O
being	O
superstitious	O
,	O
but	O
he	O
will	O
not	O
risk	O
it	O
.	O
``	O
If	O
it	O
continues	O
to	O
work	O
well	O
,	O
I	O
'll	O
stay	O
away	O
from	O
it	O
,	O
''	O
he	O
said	O
.	O
Greg	PERSON
Jarvis	PERSON
,	O
a	O
Hughes	ORGANIZATION
Aircraft	ORGANIZATION
engineer	O
on	O
loan	O
to	O
NASA	ORGANIZATION
,	O
was	O
so	O
excited	O
about	O
the	O
Challenger	O
mission	O
that	O
``	O
he	O
was	O
out	O
of	O
his	O
mind	O
,	O
''	O
his	O
father	O
remembers	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
was	O
always	O
proud	O
of	O
him	O
,	O
''	O
Jarvis	PERSON
recalled	O
,	O
adding	O
,	O
``	O
He	O
did	O
n't	O
have	O
to	O
go	O
up	O
in	O
that	O
thing	O
to	O
make	O
me	O
proud	O
.	O
''	O
Jarvis	PERSON
lost	O
his	O
composure	O
when	O
trying	O
to	O
talk	O
about	O
his	O
last	O
conversation	O
with	O
his	O
son	O
.	O
Ellen	PERSON
Jarvis	PERSON
took	O
over	O
,	O
explaining	O
that	O
``	O
Bruce	PERSON
and	O
his	O
boys	O
''	O
were	O
not	O
in	O
the	O
habit	O
of	O
sharing	O
their	O
feelings	O
about	O
each	O
other	O
.	O
``	O
In	O
his	O
last	O
brief	O
conversation	O
...	O
Greg	PERSON
said	O
,	O
`	O
I	O
love	O
you	O
dad	O
.	O
'	O
And	O
Bruce	PERSON
was	O
able	O
to	O
reply	O
,	O
`	O
I	O
love	O
you	O
son	O
--	O
I	O
'm	O
proud	O
of	O
you	O
.	O
'	O
``	O
Those	O
were	O
the	O
last	O
words	O
that	O
were	O
ever	O
said	O
,	O
''	O
Ellen	PERSON
Jarvis	PERSON
said	O
.	O
``	O
As	O
things	O
developed	O
,	O
he	O
was	O
very	O
glad	O
they	O
'd	O
had	O
those	O
words	O
.	O
''	O
NYT	O
-	O
01-26-96	DATE
1856EST	TIME

BC-SUPERCHOPPER-AZR	O
&LR;	O
01-29	DATE
BC-SUPERCHOPPER-AZR	O
CHOPPER	O
STUNT	O
WORKS	O
DESPITE	O
FEARS	O
-LRB-	O
For	O
use	O
by	O
N.Y.	ORGANIZATION
Times	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
clients	O
-RRB-	O
By	O
KARINA	PERSON
BLAND	PERSON
AND	O
MARTIN	PERSON
VAN	PERSON
DER	PERSON
WERF	PERSON
c.	O
1996	DATE
The	ORGANIZATION
Arizona	ORGANIZATION
Republic	ORGANIZATION
PHOENIX	LOCATION
--	O
No	O
question	O
,	O
it	O
was	O
an	O
awesome	O
sight	O
:	O
a	O
helicopter	O
appearing	O
seemingly	O
out	O
of	O
nowhere	O
above	O
Arizona	ORGANIZATION
State	ORGANIZATION
University	ORGANIZATION
's	O
Sun	LOCATION
Devil	LOCATION
Stadium	LOCATION
during	O
Super	O
Bowl	O
XXX	O
and	O
landing	O
lightly	O
on	O
stage	O
to	O
swoop	O
away	O
halftime	O
headliner	O
Diana	PERSON
Ross	PERSON
.	O
But	O
it	O
was	O
also	O
a	O
potentially	O
deadly	O
stunt	O
,	O
opposed	O
by	O
fire	O
and	O
safety	O
officials	O
,	O
that	O
required	O
a	O
$	MONEY
400	MONEY
million	MONEY
insurance	O
policy	O
.	O
For	O
weeks	O
,	O
National	ORGANIZATION
Football	ORGANIZATION
League	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
and	O
Super	O
Bowl	O
planners	O
debated	O
the	O
risk	O
of	O
bringing	O
the	O
helicopter	O
into	O
the	O
packed	O
stadium	O
.	O
They	O
even	O
checked	O
with	O
Gov.	O
Fife	PERSON
Symington	PERSON
,	O
who	O
gave	O
his	O
OK	O
.	O
But	O
no	O
one	O
was	O
sure	O
until	O
it	O
happened	O
that	O
it	O
could	O
be	O
pulled	O
off	O
.	O
``	O
We	O
did	O
n't	O
think	O
it	O
was	O
worth	O
it	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
Tempe	LOCATION
Fire	O
Marshal	O
Marc	PERSON
Scott	PERSON
,	O
one	O
of	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
fire	O
and	O
safety	O
officials	O
who	O
said	O
they	O
repeatedly	O
urged	O
the	O
NFL	ORGANIZATION
not	O
to	O
use	O
the	O
helicopter	O
,	O
fearing	O
for	O
the	O
safety	O
of	O
the	O
fans	O
.	O
Even	O
Ross	PERSON
was	O
a	O
little	O
apprehensive	O
about	O
it	O
and	O
considered	O
using	O
a	O
body	O
double	O
,	O
said	O
Mark	PERSON
Munhall	PERSON
,	O
who	O
headed	O
operations	O
for	O
the	O
Super	ORGANIZATION
Bowl	ORGANIZATION
Host	ORGANIZATION
Committee	ORGANIZATION
.	O
A	O
public-address	O
announcer	O
assured	O
the	O
crowd	O
several	O
times	O
,	O
``	O
This	O
stunt	O
has	O
been	O
tested	O
for	O
your	O
safety	O
.	O
Please	O
remain	O
in	O
your	O
seats	O
.	O
You	O
will	O
be	O
a	O
part	O
of	O
Super	O
Bowl	O
history	O
with	O
the	O
takeoff	O
and	O
landing	O
of	O
an	O
aircraft	O
in	O
the	O
stadium	O
.	O
''	O
But	O
out	O
of	O
sight	O
in	O
the	O
tunnel	O
at	O
the	O
north	O
end	O
zone	O
sat	O
a	O
fire	O
engine	O
and	O
a	O
``	O
brush	O
truck	O
,	O
''	O
which	O
is	O
used	O
to	O
douse	O
flames	O
quickly	O
.	O
All	O
the	O
firefighters	O
were	O
ready	O
,	O
dressed	O
in	O
full	O
gear	O
in	O
case	O
they	O
were	O
needed	O
.	O
About	O
45	O
firefighters	O
were	O
at	O
the	O
game	O
,	O
along	O
with	O
about	O
a	O
dozen	O
doctors	O
on	O
call	O
.	O
At	O
a	O
nearby	O
command	O
post	O
,	O
nurses	O
waited	O
in	O
flight	O
suits	O
.	O
If	O
anything	O
had	O
gone	O
wrong	O
,	O
triage	O
would	O
have	O
been	O
set	O
up	O
in	O
ASU	ORGANIZATION
's	O
Packard	LOCATION
Stadium	LOCATION
and	O
victims	O
taken	O
there	O
by	O
ambulance	O
.	O
The	O
helicopter	O
pilot	O
was	O
Rich	PERSON
Lee	PERSON
,	O
a	O
highly	O
decorated	O
flier	O
who	O
made	O
impressive	O
pickups	O
and	O
drop-offs	O
in	O
Vietnam	LOCATION
.	O
At	O
his	O
side	O
was	O
a	O
second	O
pilot	O
in	O
case	O
something	O
went	O
wrong	O
in	O
midflight	O
.	O
The	O
risk	O
was	O
considered	O
such	O
that	O
the	O
Host	ORGANIZATION
Committee	ORGANIZATION
took	O
out	O
a	O
$	MONEY
400	MONEY
million	MONEY
insurance	O
policy	O
for	O
the	O
helicopter	O
stunt	O
.	O
Originally	O
,	O
the	O
committee	O
thought	O
$	MONEY
100	MONEY
million	MONEY
would	O
have	O
been	O
enough	O
.	O
``	O
Here	O
comes	O
my	O
ride	O
!	O
''	O
Ross	PERSON
shouted	O
as	O
the	O
McDonnell	ORGANIZATION
Douglas	ORGANIZATION
MD	O
Explorer	O
came	O
into	O
sight	O
.	O
It	O
swept	O
over	O
the	O
edge	O
of	O
the	O
stadium	O
and	O
landed	O
on	O
a	O
dime	O
on	O
the	O
stage	O
.	O
``	O
I	O
can	O
tell	O
you	O
,	O
I	O
let	O
out	O
a	O
big	O
sigh	O
of	O
relief	O
when	O
it	O
was	O
over	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
Steve	PERSON
Patterson	PERSON
,	O
president	O
of	O
the	O
Host	ORGANIZATION
Committee	ORGANIZATION
.	O
Jim	PERSON
Steeg	PERSON
,	O
who	O
directs	O
all	O
Super	O
Bowl	O
preparations	O
for	O
the	O
NFL	ORGANIZATION
,	O
said	O
Symington	PERSON
was	O
consulted	O
because	O
of	O
the	O
state	O
's	O
potential	O
liability	O
if	O
a	O
disaster	O
had	O
occurred	O
at	O
the	O
ASU	ORGANIZATION
stadium	O
.	O
The	O
decision	O
to	O
go	O
ahead	O
was	O
made	O
Thursday	DATE
night	TIME
after	O
Symington	PERSON
,	O
ASU	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
,	O
Host	ORGANIZATION
Committee	ORGANIZATION
members	O
and	O
Neil	PERSON
Austrian	PERSON
,	O
president	O
of	O
the	O
NFL	ORGANIZATION
,	O
watched	O
eight	O
landings	O
by	O
the	O
helicopter	O
.	O
``	O
Each	O
time	O
,	O
he	O
landed	O
in	O
the	O
same	O
six-inch	O
space	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
Bill	PERSON
Shover	PERSON
,	O
chairman	O
of	O
the	O
Host	ORGANIZATION
Committee	ORGANIZATION
.	O
But	O
there	O
were	O
concerns	O
about	O
mechanical	O
failures	O
,	O
whether	O
someone	O
throwing	O
something	O
from	O
the	O
stands	O
could	O
lodge	O
in	O
the	O
rotor	O
,	O
and	O
that	O
a	O
strong	O
wind	O
could	O
toss	O
the	O
chopper	O
into	O
the	O
stands	O
.	O
``	O
We	O
measured	O
the	O
potential	O
risk	O
against	O
the	O
reward	O
,	O
and	O
all	O
the	O
odds	O
seemed	O
to	O
favor	O
the	O
reward	O
,	O
''	O
Steeg	PERSON
said	O
.	O
``	O
It	O
was	O
something	O
that	O
had	O
never	O
been	O
done	O
before	O
.	O
''	O
NYT	O
-	O
01-29-96	DATE
2158EST	TIME

BC-FIGHTER-CRASH-NYT	O
&LR;	O
01-30	DATE
BC-FIGHTER-CRASH-NYT	O
FLIER	O
KILLED	O
IN	O
NASHVILLE	LOCATION
HAD	O
EARLER	O
CRASH	O
,	O
NAVY	ORGANIZATION
SAYS	O
-LRB-	O
sw	O
-RRB-	O
By	O
ERIC	PERSON
SCHMITT	PERSON
c.	O
1996	DATE
N.Y.	ORGANIZATION
Times	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
WASHINGTON	LOCATION
--	O
The	O
flier	O
whose	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
F-14A	O
fighter	O
plunged	O
into	O
a	O
Nashville	LOCATION
suburb	O
on	O
Monday	DATE
,	O
killing	O
himself	O
and	O
four	O
other	O
people	O
,	O
crashed	O
another	O
jet	O
into	O
the	O
sea	O
last	DATE
April	DATE
.	O
But	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
investigators	O
and	O
senior	O
admirals	O
forgave	O
him	O
,	O
saying	O
he	O
made	O
a	O
mistake	O
in	O
pursuit	O
of	O
the	O
combative	O
flying	O
that	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
wants	O
and	O
encourages	O
in	O
its	O
pilots	O
.	O
The	O
flier	O
,	O
Lt.	O
Comdr	O
.	O
John	PERSON
Stacy	PERSON
Bates	PERSON
,	O
flew	O
aggressively	O
,	O
a	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
official	O
said	O
on	O
Tuesday	DATE
,	O
but	O
he	O
added	O
:	O
``	O
We	O
want	O
them	O
to	O
fly	O
aggressively	O
.	O
Bates	PERSON
was	O
highly	O
motivated	O
and	O
that	O
accident	O
was	O
a	O
one-time	O
glitch	O
on	O
his	O
record	O
.	O
He	O
was	O
a	O
great	O
aviator	O
.	O
''	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
invests	O
years	O
and	O
more	O
than	O
$	MONEY
1	MONEY
million	MONEY
to	O
train	O
each	O
of	O
its	O
fighter	O
pilots	O
,	O
and	O
is	O
reluctant	O
to	O
dismiss	O
them	O
if	O
senior	O
officers	O
believe	O
an	O
erring	O
pilot	O
can	O
learn	O
from	O
mistakes	O
.	O
But	O
as	O
military	O
investigators	O
sifted	O
through	O
the	O
wreckage	O
on	O
Tuesday	DATE
for	O
clues	O
to	O
what	O
caused	O
the	O
crash	O
that	O
killed	O
the	O
fighter	O
's	O
two-man	O
crew	O
and	O
three	O
people	O
on	O
the	O
ground	O
,	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
said	O
they	O
did	O
not	O
know	O
what	O
caused	O
Bates	PERSON
'	O
second	O
crash	O
,	O
or	O
why	O
his	O
squadron	O
had	O
lost	O
so	O
many	O
F-14	O
Tomcats	O
.	O
The	O
crash	O
was	O
the	O
fourth	O
in	O
16	O
months	O
for	O
Fighter	ORGANIZATION
Squadron	ORGANIZATION
213	ORGANIZATION
,	O
a	O
14-plane	O
unit	O
known	O
as	O
the	O
Fighting	ORGANIZATION
Blacklions	ORGANIZATION
and	O
one	O
of	O
six	O
F-14	O
squadrons	O
assigned	O
to	O
Miramar	LOCATION
Naval	LOCATION
Air	LOCATION
Station	LOCATION
near	O
San	LOCATION
Diego	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
unit	O
's	O
safety	O
record	O
is	O
by	O
far	O
the	O
worst	O
among	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
's	O
13	O
F-14	O
squadrons	O
.	O
Bates	PERSON
was	O
blamed	O
for	O
losing	O
control	O
of	O
his	O
F-14	O
last	DATE
April	DATE
while	O
conducting	O
training	O
maneuvers	O
off	O
Hawaii	LOCATION
.	O
Last	DATE
September	DATE
,	O
an	O
F-14A	O
from	O
the	O
squadron	O
exploded	O
in	O
flight	O
off	O
the	O
Philippines	LOCATION
,	O
but	O
both	O
crew	O
members	O
ejected	O
safely	O
.	O
The	O
cause	O
of	O
that	O
accident	O
is	O
still	O
under	O
investigation	O
.	O
In	O
October	DATE
1994	DATE
,	O
one	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
's	O
first	O
female	O
fighter	O
pilots	O
,	O
Lt.	O
Kara	PERSON
S.	PERSON
Hultgreen	PERSON
,	O
died	O
in	O
a	O
training	O
accident	O
off	O
Southern	LOCATION
California	LOCATION
,	O
rekindling	O
tensions	O
within	O
the	O
military	O
over	O
the	O
decision	O
to	O
expand	O
some	O
combat	O
roles	O
for	O
women	O
.	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
concluded	O
that	O
that	O
accident	O
resulted	O
from	O
a	O
combination	O
of	O
pilot	O
error	O
and	O
mechanical	O
failure	O
.	O
``	O
You	O
go	O
back	O
10	O
or	O
15	O
years	O
and	O
they	O
are	O
snake	O
bit	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
a	O
retired	O
admiral	O
who	O
once	O
commanded	O
the	O
squadron	O
.	O
``	O
We	O
've	O
tried	O
to	O
put	O
top-notch	O
pilots	O
and	O
maintenance	O
people	O
there	O
.	O
You	O
ca	O
n't	O
believe	O
in	O
luck	O
or	O
superstition	O
,	O
but	O
they	O
're	O
behind	O
the	O
eight	O
ball	O
and	O
have	O
stayed	O
there	O
.	O
''	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
ordered	O
the	O
squadron	O
to	O
suspend	O
its	O
operations	O
for	O
three	O
days	O
for	O
safety	O
reasons	O
after	O
the	O
second	O
of	O
the	O
squadron	O
's	O
four	O
crashes	O
.	O
Vice	O
Adm.	O
Brent	PERSON
Bennitt	PERSON
,	O
the	O
commander	O
of	O
naval	O
air	O
forces	O
in	O
the	O
Pacific	LOCATION
,	O
immediately	O
ordered	O
the	O
squadron	O
to	O
stand	O
down	O
again	O
after	O
the	O
crash	O
on	O
Monday	DATE
to	O
review	O
its	O
safety	O
record	O
and	O
procedures	O
.	O
The	O
crash	O
underscores	O
the	O
fact	O
that	O
even	O
in	O
peacetime	O
,	O
operating	O
complex	O
weapons	O
of	O
war	O
is	O
a	O
hazardous	O
business	O
.	O
Twelve	O
F-14	O
fliers	O
have	O
died	O
in	O
training	O
accidents	O
since	O
1992	DATE
.	O
But	O
the	O
accident	O
also	O
raises	O
questions	O
about	O
the	O
F-14	O
's	O
safety	O
record	O
.	O
Since	O
1991	DATE
,	O
the	O
fighter	O
has	O
a	O
major	O
crash	O
rate	O
of	O
5.93	O
per	O
100,000	O
flight	O
hours	O
,	O
compared	O
with	O
4.82	O
major	O
crashes	O
per	O
100,000	O
hours	O
for	O
all	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
tactical	O
aircraft	O
.	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
note	O
that	O
since	O
1981	DATE
,	O
the	O
F-14	O
's	O
major	O
accident	O
rate	O
is	O
slightly	O
lower	O
than	O
the	O
overall	O
tactical	O
aircraft	O
rate	O
.	O
Many	O
naval	O
aviators	O
have	O
complained	O
that	O
the	O
engines	O
on	O
the	O
older	O
A-model	O
F-14	O
's	O
are	O
not	O
powerful	O
enough	O
to	O
perform	O
the	O
demanding	O
aerial	O
maneuvers	O
they	O
fly	O
.	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
is	O
replacing	O
them	O
with	O
a	O
more	O
powerful	O
engine	O
that	O
is	O
now	O
on	O
about	O
30	PERCENT
percent	PERCENT
of	O
the	O
fleet	O
's	O
F-14	O
's	O
.	O
Fighter	ORGANIZATION
Squadron	ORGANIZATION
213	ORGANIZATION
flies	O
all	O
A-model	O
F-14	O
's	O
.	O
In	O
the	O
latest	O
accident	O
,	O
the	O
twin-engine	O
,	O
two-seat	O
Tomcat	O
crashed	O
shortly	O
after	O
takeoff	O
from	O
Berry	LOCATION
Field	LOCATION
,	O
an	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
National	ORGANIZATION
Guard	ORGANIZATION
airfield	O
adjacent	O
to	O
Nashville	LOCATION
International	LOCATION
Airport	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
jet	O
left	O
Miramar	LOCATION
Air	LOCATION
Station	LOCATION
in	O
San	LOCATION
Diego	LOCATION
for	O
Nashville	LOCATION
on	O
Friday	DATE
on	O
a	O
routine	O
training	O
mission	O
.	O
Bennitt	PERSON
said	O
on	O
Tuesday	DATE
that	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
approved	O
Bates	PERSON
'	O
request	O
to	O
use	O
a	O
maximum-performance	O
takeoff	O
,	O
in	O
which	O
a	O
pilot	O
turns	O
on	O
the	O
jet	O
's	O
after-burner	O
and	O
soars	O
straight	O
up	O
moments	O
after	O
the	O
aircraft	O
leaves	O
the	O
ground	O
.	O
After	O
screaming	O
up	O
through	O
the	O
clouds	O
,	O
the	O
F-14	O
then	O
came	O
straight	O
down	O
,	O
exploding	O
into	O
a	O
huge	O
fireball	O
.	O
The	O
Tomcat	O
was	O
carrying	O
16,000	O
pounds	O
of	O
fuel	O
on	O
takeoff	O
.	O
``	O
We	O
may	O
never	O
know	O
why	O
the	O
crew	O
did	O
n't	O
eject	O
,	O
''	O
Rear	O
Adm.	O
Skip	PERSON
Dirren	PERSON
told	O
reporters	O
on	O
Tuesday	DATE
morning	TIME
.	O
Newer	O
fighter	O
planes	O
do	O
have	O
recorders	O
,	O
Dirren	PERSON
said	O
,	O
but	O
they	O
were	O
not	O
included	O
when	O
the	O
F-14A	O
's	O
were	O
built	O
in	O
the	O
1970s	DATE
.	O
The	O
Grumman	ORGANIZATION
Corp.	ORGANIZATION
,	O
now	O
the	O
Northrop-Grumman	ORGANIZATION
Corp.	ORGANIZATION
,	O
manufactured	O
the	O
F-14	O
's	O
,	O
which	O
cost	O
$	MONEY
32	MONEY
million	MONEY
each	O
.	O
Killed	O
besides	O
Bates	PERSON
,	O
33	O
,	O
of	O
Chattanooga	LOCATION
,	O
Tenn.	LOCATION
,	O
was	O
the	O
jet	O
's	O
radar	O
operator	O
,	O
Lt.	O
Graham	PERSON
Alden	PERSON
Higgins	PERSON
,	O
28	O
,	O
of	O
Dover-Foxcroft	LOCATION
,	O
Maine	LOCATION
.	O
Three	O
civilians	O
were	O
also	O
killed	O
when	O
the	O
plane	O
hit	O
a	O
house	O
.	O
They	O
were	O
Elmer	PERSON
Newsom	PERSON
,	O
66	O
;	O
his	O
wife	O
,	O
Ada	PERSON
,	O
63	O
,	O
and	O
a	O
friend	O
,	O
Ewing	PERSON
T.	PERSON
Wair	PERSON
,	O
53	O
.	O
NYT	O
-	O
01-30-96	DATE
2051EST	TIME

BC-FIGHTER-CRASHES-300	O
&	O
A	O
02-04	DATE
0595	O
BC-FIGHTER-CRASHES-300	O
&	O
ADD-NYT	O
NAVY	ORGANIZATION
SQUADRON	O
COMMANDER	O
PLAGUED	O
BY	O
CRASHES	O
REASSIGNED	O
-LRB-	O
kd	O
-RRB-	O
By	O
JOHN	PERSON
O'NEIL	PERSON
c.	O
1996	DATE
N.Y.	ORGANIZATION
Times	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
WASHINGTON	LOCATION
--	O
The	O
squadron	O
commander	O
of	O
the	O
F-14	O
pilot	O
in	O
the	O
Nashville	LOCATION
crash	O
that	O
killed	O
five	O
people	O
last	DATE
week	DATE
has	O
been	O
relieved	O
of	O
his	O
command	O
,	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
announced	O
Sunday	DATE
.	O
Citing	O
three	O
accidents	O
over	O
the	O
last	DATE
year	DATE
,	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
decided	O
to	O
reassign	O
the	O
commander	O
,	O
Fred	PERSON
Kilian	PERSON
,	O
because	O
of	O
``	O
a	O
loss	O
of	O
trust	O
and	O
confidence	O
''	O
in	O
his	O
ability	O
to	O
lead	O
the	O
squadron	O
,	O
said	O
a	O
spokesman	O
,	O
Comdr	O
.	O
Gregg	PERSON
Hartung	PERSON
.	O
Fighter	ORGANIZATION
Squadron	ORGANIZATION
213	ORGANIZATION
,	O
a	O
14-plane	O
unit	O
based	O
in	O
Miramar	LOCATION
Naval	LOCATION
Base	LOCATION
near	O
San	LOCATION
Diego	LOCATION
,	O
had	O
developed	O
by	O
far	O
the	O
worst	O
safety	O
record	O
among	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
's	O
13	O
F-14	O
squadrons	O
,	O
with	O
four	O
crashes	O
over	O
the	O
last	DATE
16	DATE
months	DATE
,	O
three	O
after	O
Kilian	PERSON
became	O
its	O
leader	O
.	O
A	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officer	O
said	O
that	O
Kilian	PERSON
had	O
an	O
``	O
excellent	O
reputation	O
.	O
''	O
``	O
But	O
in	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
,	O
''	O
the	O
officer	O
said	O
,	O
speaking	O
on	O
the	O
condition	O
of	O
anonymity	O
,	O
``	O
we	O
hold	O
people	O
accountable	O
for	O
things	O
that	O
happen	O
during	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
their	O
command	O
.	O
In	O
this	O
particular	O
case	O
,	O
this	O
particular	O
squadron	O
has	O
an	O
exceptionally	O
high	O
accident	O
rate	O
--	O
higher	O
than	O
any	O
other	O
.	O
''	O
The	O
officer	O
said	O
the	O
decision	O
to	O
reassign	O
Kilian	PERSON
to	O
the	O
Pacific	LOCATION
headquarters	O
of	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
's	O
Fighter	ORGANIZATION
Wing	ORGANIZATION
was	O
made	O
Saturday	DATE
by	O
the	O
commander	O
of	O
Carrier	ORGANIZATION
Air	ORGANIZATION
Wing	ORGANIZATION
11	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Capt.	O
Dennis	PERSON
Gillespie	PERSON
.	O
Kilian	PERSON
could	O
not	O
be	O
reached	O
for	O
comment	O
.	O
In	O
the	O
latest	O
crash	O
,	O
an	O
F-14	O
from	O
Squadron	ORGANIZATION
213	ORGANIZATION
plunged	O
to	O
the	O
ground	O
immediately	O
after	O
takeoff	O
on	O
Jan.	DATE
29	DATE
,	O
killing	O
the	O
pilot	O
,	O
Lt.	O
Comdr	O
.	O
John	PERSON
Stacy	PERSON
Bates	PERSON
,	O
the	O
jet	O
's	O
radar	O
operator	O
Lt.	O
Graham	PERSON
Alden	PERSON
Higgins	PERSON
,	O
and	O
three	O
civilians	O
in	O
a	O
house	O
the	O
plane	O
crashed	O
into	O
.	O
Bates	PERSON
had	O
crashed	O
an	O
F-14	O
into	O
the	O
Pacific	LOCATION
during	O
a	O
routine	O
training	O
flight	O
in	O
April	DATE
.	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
blamed	O
him	O
for	O
causing	O
the	O
accident	O
,	O
in	O
which	O
no	O
one	O
was	O
hurt	O
,	O
by	O
losing	O
control	O
,	O
but	O
forgave	O
him	O
because	O
they	O
felt	O
he	O
was	O
displaying	O
the	O
sort	O
of	O
aggressive	O
flying	O
style	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
encourages	O
.	O
OPTIONAL	O
MATERIAL	O
FOLLOWS	O
-RRB-	O
&LR;	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officer	O
said	O
there	O
had	O
still	O
been	O
no	O
determination	O
of	O
a	O
cause	O
of	O
the	O
Nashville	LOCATION
crash	O
.	O
Bates	PERSON
had	O
requested	O
and	O
been	O
given	O
permission	O
for	O
``	O
an	O
unrestricted	O
climb	O
to	O
15,000	O
feet	O
''	O
--	O
a	O
style	O
of	O
takeoff	O
in	O
which	O
the	O
pilot	O
soars	O
straight	O
up	O
moments	O
after	O
leaving	O
the	O
ground	O
.	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officer	O
declined	O
to	O
comment	O
on	O
whether	O
the	O
unrestricted	O
climb	O
could	O
be	O
linked	O
to	O
the	O
crash	O
.	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officer	O
confirmed	O
that	O
the	O
pilot	O
's	O
parents	O
had	O
been	O
at	O
Berry	LOCATION
Field	LOCATION
,	O
an	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
National	ORGANIZATION
Guard	ORGANIZATION
airfield	O
adjacent	O
to	O
Nashville	LOCATION
International	LOCATION
Airport	LOCATION
watching	O
the	O
takeoff	O
.	O
Flying	O
fighter	O
planes	O
is	O
a	O
dangerous	O
business	O
,	O
even	O
in	O
peacetime	O
:	O
since	O
1992	DATE
,	O
12	O
F-14	O
pilots	O
have	O
died	O
in	O
training	O
accidents	O
.	O
But	O
over	O
the	O
years	O
,	O
many	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
pilots	O
have	O
complained	O
that	O
the	O
engines	O
on	O
A-model	O
F-14s	O
,	O
like	O
all	O
the	O
planes	O
in	O
Squadron	ORGANIZATION
213	ORGANIZATION
,	O
are	O
not	O
powerful	O
enough	O
for	O
the	O
maneuvers	O
they	O
are	O
asked	O
to	O
perform	O
.	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
have	O
begun	O
to	O
replace	O
them	O
with	O
more	O
powerful	O
models	O
.	O
Squadron	ORGANIZATION
213	ORGANIZATION
's	O
string	O
of	O
crashes	O
began	O
in	O
October	DATE
1994	DATE
,	O
before	O
Kilian	PERSON
took	O
over	O
,	O
when	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
's	O
first	O
female	O
fighter	O
pilots	O
,	O
Lt.	O
Kara	PERSON
S.	PERSON
Hultgreen	PERSON
,	O
died	O
in	O
a	O
training	O
accident	O
off	O
Southern	LOCATION
California	LOCATION
.	O
In	O
addition	O
to	O
the	O
Nashville	LOCATION
crash	O
and	O
Bates	PERSON
's	O
April	DATE
accident	O
,	O
an	O
F-14	O
from	O
Squadron	ORGANIZATION
213	ORGANIZATION
also	O
exploded	O
last	DATE
September	DATE
without	O
fatalities	O
just	O
after	O
taking	O
off	O
from	O
an	O
aircraft	O
carrier	O
.	O
After	O
last	DATE
week	DATE
's	O
accident	O
,	O
the	O
squadron	O
was	O
ordered	O
to	O
stop	O
flying	O
while	O
its	O
safety	O
procedures	O
were	O
reviewed	O
.	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
spokesman	O
,	O
Hartung	PERSON
,	O
said	O
that	O
order	O
remained	O
in	O
effect	O
.	O
NYT	O
-	O
02-04-96	DATE
1947EST	TIME

BC-CRASH-AVIATION-KAN	O
&LR;	O
02-06	DATE
BC-CRASH-AVIATION-KAN	O
SAFETY	O
OF	O
MILITARY	O
AVIATION	O
IMPROVING	O
,	O
STUDY	O
SUGGESTS	O
-LRB-	O
For	O
use	O
by	O
New	ORGANIZATION
York	ORGANIZATION
Times	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
clients	O
-RRB-	O
By	O
JAMES	PERSON
KUHNHENN	PERSON
c.	O
1996	DATE
Kansas	ORGANIZATION
City	ORGANIZATION
Star	ORGANIZATION
WASHINGTON	LOCATION
--	O
The	O
number	O
of	O
military	O
aircraft	O
accidents	O
has	O
dropped	O
dramatically	O
in	O
the	O
last	DATE
20	DATE
years	DATE
,	O
making	O
the	O
rate	O
of	O
fatalities	O
in	O
military	O
plane	O
crashes	O
comparable	O
to	O
that	O
of	O
commercial	O
airliners	O
.	O
Still	O
,	O
such	O
accidents	O
cost	O
the	O
Pentagon	ORGANIZATION
more	O
than	O
$	MONEY
1	MONEY
billion	MONEY
a	O
year	O
,	O
suggesting	O
that	O
while	O
crashes	O
have	O
declined	O
,	O
the	O
cost	O
per	O
accident	O
has	O
increased	O
significantly	O
.	O
Congressional	O
investigators	O
,	O
in	O
a	O
report	O
released	O
Monday	DATE
,	O
found	O
that	O
the	O
number	O
of	O
major	O
accidents	O
dropped	O
from	O
309	O
in	O
1975	DATE
to	O
76	O
last	DATE
year	DATE
.	O
Likewise	O
,	O
the	O
number	O
of	O
deaths	O
dropped	O
from	O
285	O
to	O
85	O
.	O
``	O
While	O
1995	DATE
was	O
the	O
safest	O
year	O
in	O
military	O
aviation	O
history	O
,	O
there	O
is	O
room	O
for	O
improvement	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
Rep.	O
Ike	PERSON
Skelton	PERSON
of	O
Missouri	LOCATION
,	O
who	O
requested	O
the	O
study	O
.	O
``	O
One	O
crash	O
is	O
too	O
many	O
;	O
one	O
death	O
is	O
too	O
many	O
.	O
''	O
In	O
an	O
otherwise	O
upbeat	O
report	O
,	O
the	O
study	O
by	O
the	O
congressional	O
General	ORGANIZATION
Accounting	ORGANIZATION
Office	ORGANIZATION
did	O
question	O
the	O
process	O
by	O
which	O
the	O
military	O
investigates	O
such	O
crashes	O
and	O
Skelton	PERSON
recommended	O
ways	O
to	O
make	O
investigative	O
boards	O
more	O
independent	O
from	O
commanding	O
officers	O
.	O
Coincidentally	O
,	O
the	O
report	O
came	O
just	O
days	O
after	O
an	O
F-14A	O
``	O
Tomcat	O
''	O
fighter	O
jet	O
crashed	O
in	O
Nashville	LOCATION
,	O
Tenn.	LOCATION
,	O
killing	O
two	O
crew	O
members	O
and	O
three	O
persons	O
on	O
the	O
ground	O
.	O
The	O
cause	O
of	O
that	O
accident	O
is	O
under	O
investigation	O
and	O
was	O
not	O
included	O
in	O
the	O
data	O
analyzed	O
by	O
the	O
GAO	ORGANIZATION
.	O
The	O
GAO	ORGANIZATION
investigators	O
did	O
conclude	O
that	O
human	O
error	O
accounted	O
for	O
73	PERCENT
percent	PERCENT
of	O
the	O
military	O
aircraft	O
accidents	O
in	O
1994	DATE
and	O
last	DATE
year	DATE
.	O
That	O
number	O
is	O
comparable	O
with	O
the	O
rate	O
of	O
human	O
error	O
in	O
commercial	O
flight	O
accidents	O
,	O
according	O
to	O
National	ORGANIZATION
Transportation	ORGANIZATION
Safety	ORGANIZATION
Board	ORGANIZATION
spokesman	O
Michael	PERSON
Benson	PERSON
.	O
According	O
to	O
GAO	ORGANIZATION
investigators	O
,	O
the	O
rate	O
of	O
fatalities	O
per	O
100,000	O
flying	O
hours	O
dropped	O
from	O
about	O
4	O
in	O
1975	DATE
to	O
1.7	O
last	DATE
year	DATE
.	O
Significantly	O
,	O
however	O
,	O
the	O
rate	O
of	O
fatalities	O
in	O
commercial	O
carriers	O
has	O
been	O
no	O
higher	O
than	O
1.4	O
since	O
1982	DATE
and	O
was	O
1.2	O
last	DATE
year	DATE
,	O
according	O
to	O
NTSB	ORGANIZATION
data	O
.	O
The	O
study	O
did	O
not	O
include	O
crashes	O
or	O
fatalities	O
involving	O
combat	O
and	O
focused	O
on	O
accidents	O
that	O
caused	O
death	O
or	O
permanent	O
injury	O
,	O
or	O
destroyed	O
or	O
severely	O
damaged	O
an	O
aircraft	O
.	O
Over	O
the	O
20-year	O
period	O
of	O
the	O
study	O
,	O
military	O
aircraft	O
were	O
involved	O
in	O
3,828	O
accidents	O
,	O
killing	O
3,819	O
persons	O
and	O
destroying	O
3,483	O
of	O
the	O
aircraft	O
.	O
Skelton	PERSON
requested	O
the	O
GAO	ORGANIZATION
study	O
last	DATE
May	DATE
after	O
a	O
succession	O
of	O
five	O
military	O
airplanes	O
crashes	O
killed	O
18	O
persons	O
within	O
five	O
weeks	O
.	O
The	O
study	O
also	O
came	O
amid	O
reports	O
that	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
Force	ORGANIZATION
commanders	O
falsified	O
crash	O
investigative	O
files	O
to	O
avoid	O
embarrassment	O
in	O
about	O
30	O
cases	O
.	O
The	O
results	O
of	O
an	O
investigation	O
by	O
the	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
Force	ORGANIZATION
inspector	O
general	O
are	O
under	O
review	O
.	O
GAO	ORGANIZATION
investigators	O
concluded	O
that	O
despite	O
past	O
entreaties	O
to	O
the	O
armed	O
forces	O
to	O
give	O
their	O
investigative	O
boards	O
greater	O
independence	O
,	O
movement	O
toward	O
that	O
end	O
has	O
been	O
slow	O
.	O
Until	O
recently	O
,	O
only	O
the	O
Army	ORGANIZATION
required	O
that	O
its	O
investigative	O
board	O
include	O
a	O
voting	O
member	O
from	O
outside	O
the	O
Army	ORGANIZATION
chain	O
of	O
command	O
.	O
The	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
Force	ORGANIZATION
,	O
after	O
convening	O
a	O
commission	O
to	O
improve	O
crash	O
investigations	O
,	O
decided	O
only	O
in	O
September	DATE
to	O
add	O
an	O
independent	O
voice	O
to	O
its	O
investigative	O
board	O
.	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
,	O
meanwhile	O
,	O
has	O
not	O
taken	O
any	O
steps	O
to	O
make	O
its	O
board	O
more	O
independent	O
.	O
``	O
This	O
creates	O
,	O
at	O
a	O
minimum	O
,	O
the	O
appearance	O
that	O
investigations	O
are	O
not	O
completely	O
independent	O
,	O
''	O
Skelton	PERSON
said	O
.	O
With	O
his	O
changes	O
,	O
he	O
said	O
,	O
``	O
no	O
one	O
could	O
say	O
someone	O
in	O
the	O
chain	O
of	O
command	O
is	O
not	O
going	O
to	O
call	O
a	O
pilot	O
a	O
hot	O
dog	O
.	O
''	O
NYT	O
-	O
02-06-96	DATE
1934EST	TIME

BC	O
-	O
BOEING	ORGANIZATION
-	O
CRASH-SPI	O
&LR;	O
02-07	DATE
BC	O
-	O
BOEING	ORGANIZATION
-	O
CRASH-SPI	O
BOEING	ORGANIZATION
TEAM	O
GEARS	O
UP	O
TO	O
AID	O
CRASH	O
INVESTIGATION	O
-LRB-	O
For	O
use	O
by	O
New	ORGANIZATION
York	ORGANIZATION
Times	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
clients	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
By	O
KAREN	PERSON
WEST	PERSON
c.	O
1996	DATE
Seattle	ORGANIZATION
Post-Intelligencer	ORGANIZATION
SEATTLE	LOCATION
--	O
It	O
's	O
the	O
phone	O
call	O
no	O
one	O
wants	O
to	O
get	O
,	O
but	O
everyone	O
knows	O
might	O
come	O
one	O
day	O
.	O
It	O
came	O
late	DATE
Tuesday	DATE
when	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
got	O
word	O
that	O
a	O
chartered	O
757	O
aircraft	O
crashed	O
shortly	O
after	O
takeoff	O
from	O
the	O
Dominican	LOCATION
Republic	LOCATION
.	O
All	O
189	O
passengers	O
are	O
feared	O
dead	O
.	O
The	O
crash	O
,	O
only	O
the	O
second	O
in	O
the	O
history	O
of	O
the	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
757	O
,	O
came	O
less	DATE
than	DATE
two	DATE
months	DATE
after	DATE
an	DATE
American	ORGANIZATION
Airlines	ORGANIZATION
757	O
slammed	O
into	O
a	O
mountain	O
as	O
it	O
approached	O
Cali	LOCATION
,	O
Colombia	LOCATION
.	O
Four	O
people	O
survived	O
the	O
Dec.	DATE
20	DATE
crash	O
that	O
killed	O
160	O
people	O
.	O
The	O
cause	O
has	O
not	O
yet	O
been	O
determined	O
.	O
After	O
hearing	O
the	O
news	O
of	O
Alas	ORGANIZATION
Nacionales	ORGANIZATION
Flight	O
301	O
Tuesday	DATE
night	TIME
,	O
members	O
of	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
's	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
Safety	ORGANIZATION
Investigation	ORGANIZATION
Group	ORGANIZATION
monitored	O
the	O
situation	O
throughout	TIME
the	TIME
night	TIME
and	O
quickly	O
assembled	O
a	O
team	O
of	O
safety	O
experts	O
to	O
be	O
on	O
standby	O
in	O
case	O
they	O
were	O
needed	O
at	O
the	O
crash	O
scene	O
.	O
One	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
air	O
safety	O
investigator	O
was	O
expected	O
to	O
arrive	O
Thursday	DATE
in	O
Puerto	LOCATION
Plata	LOCATION
to	O
assist	O
a	O
team	O
from	O
the	O
National	ORGANIZATION
Transportation	ORGANIZATION
Safety	ORGANIZATION
Board	ORGANIZATION
and	O
the	O
Dominican	LOCATION
Republic	LOCATION
in	O
trying	O
to	O
determine	O
why	O
the	O
two-engine	O
jet	O
crashed	O
.	O
More	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
engineers	O
will	O
be	O
called	O
in	O
if	O
needed	O
.	O
When	O
an	O
accident	O
occurs	O
,	O
government	O
investigative	O
agencies	O
--	O
such	O
as	O
the	O
NTSB	ORGANIZATION
for	O
U.S.	LOCATION
carriers	O
--	O
are	O
responsible	O
for	O
determining	O
what	O
went	O
wrong	O
.	O
The	O
NTSB	ORGANIZATION
usually	O
invites	O
the	O
aircraft	O
's	O
manufacturer	O
,	O
in	O
this	O
case	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
,	O
to	O
help	O
search	O
for	O
clues	O
and	O
to	O
provide	O
techical	O
support	O
if	O
needed	O
.	O
A	O
typical	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
team	O
,	O
whose	O
members	O
are	O
assigned	O
to	O
aircraft	O
crashes	O
on	O
a	O
rotating	O
basis	O
,	O
usually	O
includes	O
an	O
accident	O
investigator	O
,	O
a	O
pilot	O
and	O
a	O
structures	O
expert	O
.	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
investigators	O
typically	O
help	O
gather	O
evidence	O
,	O
conduct	O
engineering	O
analysis	O
and	O
,	O
if	O
needed	O
,	O
reconstruct	O
major	O
portions	O
of	O
the	O
airplane	O
from	O
the	O
wreckage	O
.	O
Until	O
the	O
supervising	O
agency	O
has	O
completed	O
its	O
accident	O
investigation	O
and	O
issued	O
its	O
final	O
report	O
,	O
the	O
company	O
is	O
prohibited	O
from	O
commenting	O
on	O
the	O
investigation	O
findings	O
.	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
spokesman	O
Russ	PERSON
Young	PERSON
said	O
the	O
aircraft	O
involved	O
in	O
Tuesday	DATE
's	O
crash	O
was	O
delivered	O
to	O
Eastern	ORGANIZATION
Airlines	ORGANIZATION
in	O
February	DATE
1985	DATE
and	O
was	O
powered	O
by	O
Rolls-Royce	ORGANIZATION
Plc	ORGANIZATION
RB-211	O
engines	O
.	O
The	O
jetliner	O
was	O
the	O
31st	O
off	O
the	O
assembly	O
line	O
,	O
out	O
of	O
a	O
total	O
694	O
produced	O
to	O
date	O
,	O
Young	PERSON
said	O
.	O
As	O
of	O
November	DATE
1995	DATE
,	O
the	O
plane	O
had	O
29,000	O
flight	O
hours	O
and	O
13,400	O
takeoff\/landing	O
cycles	O
.	O
Plans	O
for	O
the	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
757	O
's	O
development	O
began	O
in	O
1978	DATE
.	O
It	O
was	O
first	O
flown	O
March	DATE
28	DATE
,	DATE
1982	DATE
,	O
and	O
it	O
entered	O
commercial	O
service	O
with	O
Eastern	ORGANIZATION
Airlines	ORGANIZATION
on	O
Jan.	DATE
1	DATE
,	DATE
1983	DATE
.	O
The	O
757	O
is	O
a	O
twin-engine	O
,	O
medium	O
-	O
to	O
long-range	O
jetliner	O
that	O
can	O
carry	O
up	O
to	O
239	O
passengers	O
,	O
depending	O
on	O
cabin	O
configuration	O
.	O
According	O
to	O
Boeing	ORGANIZATION
,	O
the	O
worldwide	O
fleet	O
of	O
757s	O
has	O
carried	O
more	O
than	O
565	O
million	O
passengers	O
since	DATE
entering	DATE
commercial	DATE
service	DATE
.	O
NYT	O
-	O
02-07-96	DATE
2110EST	TIME

BC-SEEING-FOG-CLEARLY-PA	O
02-16	DATE
1384	O
BC-SEEING-FOG-CLEARLY-PAGEUP-NYTSF	O
THE	O
MYSTERY	O
AND	O
MENACE	O
OF	O
FOG	O
Includes	O
a	O
300-word	O
sidebar	O
By	O
JOSEPH	PERSON
STOCKER	PERSON
c.	O
1995	DATE
The	O
Rotarian	ORGANIZATION
magazine	O
-LRB-	O
This	O
``	O
separate	O
buy	O
''	O
article	O
is	O
from	O
this	DATE
week	DATE
's	O
PageUp	O
Lifestyle	O
and	O
Entertainment	O
Package	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
-LRB-	O
She	O
also	O
has	O
information	O
on	O
how	O
to	O
subscribe	O
to	O
PageUp	O
,	O
a	O
weekly	O
package	O
of	O
eight	O
intriguing	O
articles	O
with	O
color	O
art	O
.	O
Note	O
:	O
On	O
February	DATE
12	DATE
,	DATE
1996	DATE
,	O
11	O
people	O
were	O
killed	O
in	O
a	O
300-car	O
crash	O
on	O
a	O
foggy	O
highway	O
between	O
Milan	LOCATION
and	O
Trieste	LOCATION
.	O
This	O
rush-hour	O
disaster	O
was	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
deadliest	O
episodes	O
in	O
Italy	LOCATION
's	O
history	O
of	O
fog-related	O
accidents	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
Author	O
Carl	PERSON
Sandburg	PERSON
described	O
it	O
as	O
coming	O
in	O
``	O
on	O
little	O
cat	O
's	O
feet	O
.	O
''	O
Charles	PERSON
Dickens	PERSON
,	O
taking	O
an	O
understandably	O
dim	O
view	O
of	O
a	O
legendary	O
London	LOCATION
``	O
pea-souper	O
,	O
''	O
or	O
fog	O
laced	O
with	O
industrial	O
soot	O
,	O
proclaimed	O
that	O
the	O
skies	O
had	O
``	O
gone	O
into	O
mourning	O
for	O
the	O
death	O
of	O
the	O
sun	O
.	O
''	O
Taking	O
a	O
cheerier	O
view	O
,	O
children	O
's	O
-	O
book	O
author	O
Susi	PERSON
Gregg	PERSON
Fowler	PERSON
has	O
likened	O
fog	O
to	O
a	O
``	O
cloud	O
of	O
silver	O
cotton	O
candy	O
.	O
''	O
Indeed	O
,	O
fog	O
is	O
just	O
a	O
``	O
cloud	O
intersecting	O
the	O
ground	O
,	O
''	O
in	O
the	O
words	O
of	O
Arizona	ORGANIZATION
State	ORGANIZATION
climatologist	O
Anthony	PERSON
Brazel	PERSON
,	O
produced	O
by	O
warm	O
,	O
moist	O
air	O
touching	O
a	O
cool	O
surface	O
--	O
land	O
or	O
water	O
.	O
The	O
air	O
is	O
cooled	O
to	O
``	O
dew	O
point	O
''	O
and	O
the	O
moisture	O
is	O
condensed	O
into	O
liquid	O
droplets	O
.	O
These	O
droplets	O
coalesce	O
around	O
microscopic	O
nuclei	O
.	O
So	O
minuscule	O
are	O
fog	O
droplets	O
that	O
it	O
takes	O
billions	O
to	O
fill	O
a	O
teaspoon	O
.	O
A	O
U.S.	ORGANIZATION
Coast	ORGANIZATION
Guard	ORGANIZATION
bulletin	O
noted	O
that	O
``	O
a	O
block	O
of	O
fog	O
three	O
feet	O
wide	O
,	O
six	O
feet	O
high	O
and	O
100	O
feet	O
long	O
equals	O
less	O
than	O
one-seventh	O
of	O
a	O
cup	O
of	O
water	O
.	O
''	O
On	O
the	O
coast	O
of	O
Chile	LOCATION
,	O
the	O
arid	O
mountain	O
village	O
of	O
Chungungo	LOCATION
was	O
forever	O
short	O
of	O
water	O
,	O
which	O
had	O
to	O
be	O
trucked	O
in	O
over	O
13	O
miles	O
of	O
dirt	O
roads	O
.	O
Today	DATE
the	O
300-plus	O
villagers	O
have	O
plenty	O
of	O
water	O
,	O
thanks	O
to	O
fog	O
.	O
On	O
the	O
slopes	O
of	O
a	O
mountain	O
rising	O
above	O
Chungungo	LOCATION
,	O
Chilean	O
and	O
Canadian	O
scientists	O
erected	O
75	O
nets	O
held	O
in	O
place	O
by	O
eucalyptus	O
poles	O
.	O
About	O
one-third	O
of	O
the	O
fog	O
's	O
tiny	O
water	O
particles	O
hit	O
the	O
net	O
's	O
fibers	O
and	O
coalesce	O
into	O
water	O
droplets	O
.	O
Then	O
the	O
droplets	O
trickle	O
into	O
troughs	O
and	O
the	O
water	O
--	O
remarkably	O
pure	O
--	O
flows	O
to	O
a	O
25,000-gallon	O
tank	O
.	O
There	O
is	O
little	O
rainfall	O
on	O
the	O
volcanic	O
peaks	O
rising	O
out	O
of	O
the	O
Chalbi	LOCATION
Desert	LOCATION
in	O
Kenya	LOCATION
,	O
yet	O
lush	O
jungles	O
exist	O
on	O
the	O
mountain	O
slopes	O
.	O
Fog	O
covers	O
the	O
mountains	O
for	O
several	O
hours	O
a	O
day	O
,	O
watering	O
the	O
green	O
growth	O
.	O
We	O
can	O
sometimes	O
use	O
fog	O
,	O
but	O
we	O
ca	O
n't	O
control	O
it	O
.	O
On	O
July	DATE
26	DATE
,	DATE
1956	DATE
,	O
the	O
Italian	O
luxury	O
liner	O
Andrea	O
Doria	O
emerged	O
suddenly	O
from	O
a	O
fog	O
bank	O
off	O
the	O
Massachusetts	LOCATION
coast	O
,	O
crashed	O
into	O
the	O
Swedish	O
liner	O
Stockholm	O
and	O
sank	O
,	O
killing	O
52	O
people	O
.	O
The	O
worst	O
London	LOCATION
fog	O
of	O
all	O
--	O
a	O
lethal	O
mix	O
of	O
fog	O
and	O
industrial	O
pollutants	O
--	O
descended	O
in	O
December	DATE
1952	DATE
.	O
As	O
a	O
consequence	O
,	O
an	O
estimated	O
4,000	O
people	O
died	O
of	O
bronchitis	O
or	O
pneumonia	O
.	O
A	O
similar	O
tragedy	O
happened	O
in	O
Donora	LOCATION
,	O
Penn	LOCATION
.	LOCATION
,	O
in	O
1948	DATE
,	O
when	O
fog	O
mixed	O
with	O
smog	O
from	O
railroad	O
engines	O
,	O
manufacturing	O
plants	O
and	O
steamboats	O
on	O
the	O
Monongahela	LOCATION
River	LOCATION
.	O
Nearly	O
one	O
of	O
every	O
two	O
citizens	O
of	O
Donora	LOCATION
became	O
ill	O
,	O
and	O
20	O
died	O
.	O
Fog	O
makes	O
highway	O
driving	O
hazardous	O
.	O
One	O
chain-reaction	O
collision	O
on	O
a	O
foggy	O
German	O
autobahn	O
made	O
scrap	O
metal	O
out	O
of	O
118	O
cars	O
.	O
Pileups	O
of	O
as	O
many	O
as	O
200	O
cars	O
have	O
occurred	O
in	O
Brazil	LOCATION
and	O
Denmark	LOCATION
.	O
In	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
,	O
the	O
worst	O
winter	O
for	O
fog-induced	O
chain-reaction	O
tragedies	O
was	O
in	O
1990-1991	DATE
.	O
Four	O
pileups	O
in	O
Tennessee	LOCATION
,	O
Utah	LOCATION
and	O
California	LOCATION
involved	O
238	O
vehicles	O
,	O
resulting	O
in	O
21	O
deaths	O
and	O
more	O
than	O
90	O
injuries	O
.	O
When	O
airports	O
are	O
blanketed	O
with	O
heavy	O
fog	O
,	O
airline	O
companies	O
--	O
and	O
inevitably	O
passengers	O
--	O
pay	O
a	O
heavy	O
price	O
for	O
delays	O
.	O
This	O
occurs	O
in	O
spite	O
of	O
radar	O
,	O
autopilot	O
and	O
all	O
the	O
rest	O
of	O
the	O
complex	O
modern	O
navigation	O
and	O
communication	O
devices	O
in	O
use	O
.	O
``	O
Obviously	O
,	O
if	O
you	O
ca	O
n't	O
see	O
the	O
runway	O
,	O
it	O
's	O
very	O
difficult	O
to	O
land	O
,	O
''	O
says	O
meteorologist	O
Tim	PERSON
McClung	PERSON
of	O
the	O
Los	LOCATION
Angeles	LOCATION
office	O
of	O
the	O
National	ORGANIZATION
Weather	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
in	O
Oxnard	LOCATION
,	O
Calif.	LOCATION
``	O
The	O
biggest	O
challenge	O
for	O
pilots	O
and	O
air-traffic	O
controllers	O
,	O
''	O
McClung	PERSON
says	O
,	O
``	O
is	O
looking	O
at	O
the	O
current	O
weather	O
and	O
deciding	O
whether	O
an	O
aircraft	O
can	O
make	O
it	O
in	O
safely	O
or	O
not	O
.	O
``	O
One	O
of	O
the	O
problems	O
with	O
fog	O
is	O
that	O
it	O
comes	O
and	O
goes	O
.	O
You	O
can	O
have	O
a	O
plane	O
coming	O
and	O
it	O
looks	O
pretty	O
good	O
10	O
miles	O
out	O
,	O
and	O
by	O
the	O
time	O
the	O
plane	O
is	O
ready	O
to	O
land	O
,	O
the	O
fog	O
has	O
come	O
in	O
again	O
.	O
''	O
What	O
can	O
be	O
done	O
about	O
fog	O
that	O
pollutes	O
and	O
makes	O
travel	O
dangerous	O
?	O
London	LOCATION
has	O
long	O
since	O
cleaned	O
up	O
its	O
act	O
,	O
banning	O
the	O
burning	O
of	O
soft	O
coal	O
and	O
greatly	O
reducing	O
smokestack	O
emissions	O
.	O
The	O
city	O
still	O
has	O
fog	O
,	O
but	O
it	O
's	O
not	O
deadly	O
.	O
Even	O
songbirds	O
missing	O
from	O
the	O
city	O
for	O
nearly	O
a	O
century	O
have	O
returned	O
.	O
During	O
World	O
War	O
II	O
,	O
the	O
British	O
developed	O
Fog	O
Investigation	O
and	O
Dispersal	O
Operation	O
,	O
which	O
required	O
the	O
burning	O
of	O
gasoline	O
along	O
runways	O
to	O
dispel	O
the	O
fog	O
and	O
facilitate	O
landings	O
.	O
But	O
it	O
was	O
expensive	O
and	O
hair-raising	O
for	O
pilots	O
to	O
land	O
between	O
the	O
flames	O
.	O
At	O
Orly	LOCATION
and	O
DeGaulle	LOCATION
airports	O
near	O
Paris	LOCATION
,	O
the	O
French	O
have	O
installed	O
a	O
system	O
called	O
Turboclair	O
--	O
jet	O
engines	O
channeling	O
exhaust	O
heat	O
across	O
the	O
approach	O
end	O
of	O
a	O
runway	O
.	O
Los	LOCATION
Angeles	LOCATION
International	LOCATION
Airport	LOCATION
,	O
however	O
,	O
has	O
dismissed	O
the	O
idea	O
as	O
too	O
costly	O
and	O
not	O
sufficiently	O
effective	O
.	O
Most	O
airports	O
today	DATE
eliminate	O
fog	O
by	O
``	O
seeding	O
''	O
it	O
.	O
Airplanes	O
are	O
sent	O
up	O
to	O
disperse	O
it	O
,	O
using	O
substances	O
such	O
as	O
silver	O
iodide	O
or	O
solidified	O
carbon	O
dioxide	O
-LRB-	O
dry	O
ice	O
-RRB-	O
.	O
The	O
fog	O
droplets	O
coalesce	O
around	O
these	O
substances	O
and	O
fall	O
to	O
the	O
ground	O
,	O
looking	O
a	O
little	O
like	O
snow	O
.	O
The	O
fog	O
lifts	O
,	O
at	O
least	O
long	O
enough	O
for	O
a	O
plane	O
or	O
two	O
to	O
land	O
.	O
What	O
to	O
do	O
about	O
fog-shrouded	O
seacoasts	O
?	O
Radar	O
,	O
foghorns	O
and	O
lighthouses	O
.	O
Fog-shrouded	O
highways	O
?	O
The	O
experts	O
have	O
n't	O
been	O
able	O
to	O
do	O
much	O
more	O
than	O
post	O
warnings	O
and	O
give	O
motorists	O
advice	O
--	O
use	O
your	O
low-beam	O
lights	O
or	O
fog	O
lights	O
and	O
get	O
off	O
the	O
road	O
if	O
you	O
can	O
.	O
So	O
at	O
the	O
same	O
time	O
humans	O
benefit	O
from	O
fog	O
in	O
Chile	LOCATION
and	O
Africa	LOCATION
,	O
we	O
continue	O
to	O
fight	O
it	O
at	O
airports	O
,	O
on	O
seacoasts	O
and	O
on	O
highways	O
.	O
Will	O
we	O
ever	O
win	O
the	O
battle	O
?	O
We	O
have	O
n't	O
the	O
foggiest	O
.	O
SIDEBAR	O
:	O
TYPES	O
OF	O
FOG	O
Radiation	O
fog	O
usually	O
occurs	O
at	O
night	O
or	O
just	O
before	O
dawn	O
,	O
when	O
the	O
air	O
is	O
moist	O
and	O
still	O
.	O
An	O
absence	O
of	O
cloud	O
cover	O
allows	O
heat	O
to	O
escape	O
from	O
the	O
earth	O
's	O
surface	O
.	O
When	O
the	O
saturated	O
air	O
touches	O
the	O
chilled	O
land	O
,	O
radiation	O
fog	O
forms	O
.	O
It	O
usually	O
disperses	O
by	O
sunrise	O
.	O
Radiation	O
fog	O
develops	O
on	O
clear	O
,	O
calm	O
nights	O
,	O
mostly	O
in	O
areas	O
where	O
there	O
is	O
much	O
moisture	O
,	O
such	O
as	O
river	O
valleys	O
,	O
lakes	O
and	O
harbors	O
.	O
Upslope	O
fog	O
is	O
sometimes	O
called	O
``	O
Cheyenne	LOCATION
''	O
fog	O
because	O
it	O
typically	O
forms	O
on	O
the	O
eastern	O
slopes	O
of	O
the	O
Rocky	LOCATION
Mountains	LOCATION
.	O
Warm	O
tropical	O
air	O
from	O
the	O
Gulf	LOCATION
of	LOCATION
Mexico	LOCATION
spreads	O
up	O
the	O
mountains	O
and	O
cools	O
.	O
Dew	O
point	O
is	O
reached	O
,	O
fog	O
forms	O
and	O
Cheyenne	LOCATION
and	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
other	O
towns	O
get	O
misty	O
.	O
``	O
Sea	O
smoke	O
''	O
or	O
``	O
vapor	O
,	O
''	O
as	O
Maine	LOCATION
fishermen	O
call	O
it	O
,	O
is	O
the	O
opposite	O
of	O
upslope	O
fog	O
and	O
occurs	O
when	O
cold	O
air	O
passes	O
from	O
the	O
land	O
over	O
relatively	O
warm	O
coastal	O
waters	O
.	O
In	O
northern	O
climates	O
,	O
sea	O
smoke	O
sometimes	O
leaves	O
a	O
coating	O
of	O
frost	O
on	O
people	O
,	O
tree	O
branches	O
and	O
other	O
objects	O
near	O
the	O
water	O
.	O
Advection	O
fog	O
occurs	O
when	O
moisture-laden	O
air	O
comes	O
in	O
from	O
the	O
ocean	O
and	O
hits	O
the	O
colder	O
surface	O
waters	O
off	O
the	O
coast	O
.	O
Advection	O
fog	O
rolls	O
into	O
San	LOCATION
Francisco	LOCATION
almost	O
every	O
day	O
,	O
shrouding	O
the	O
Golden	O
Gate	O
Bridge	O
,	O
delighting	O
tourists	O
and	O
prompting	O
police	O
and	O
cable-car	O
drivers	O
to	O
put	O
on	O
their	O
yellow	O
slickers	O
.	O
The	O
same	O
fog	O
probably	O
caused	O
Sir	O
Francis	PERSON
Drake	PERSON
to	O
miss	O
San	LOCATION
Francisco	LOCATION
Bay	LOCATION
when	O
he	O
came	O
down	O
the	O
coast	O
in	O
his	O
square-rigger	O
Golden	O
Hind	O
400	DATE
years	DATE
ago	DATE
.	O
Smog	O
is	O
fog	O
made	O
heavier	O
and	O
darker	O
as	O
a	O
result	O
of	O
large	O
amounts	O
of	O
air	O
pollutants	O
.	O
This	O
photochemical	O
haze	O
that	O
plagues	O
many	O
large	O
urban	O
centers	O
is	O
caused	O
by	O
the	O
action	O
of	O
solar	O
ultraviolet	O
radiation	O
on	O
an	O
atmosphere	O
polluted	O
with	O
hydrocarbons	O
and	O
nitrogen	O
oxides	O
from	O
automobile	O
exhaust	O
.	O
-LRB-	O
Joseph	PERSON
Stocker	PERSON
is	O
a	O
Phoenix	LOCATION
-	O
based	O
free-lance	O
writer	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
-------------------------------------------------	O
NYT	O
-	O
02-16-96	DATE
1257EST	TIME

BC-TRAVEL-NOTES-BOS	O
&LR;	O
02-27	DATE
BC-TRAVEL-NOTES-BOS	O
WOW	O
,	O
WHAT	O
A	O
HONEYMOON	O
!	O
-LRB-	O
For	O
use	O
by	O
New	ORGANIZATION
York	ORGANIZATION
Times	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
clients	O
-RRB-	O
By	O
RICHARD	PERSON
P.	PERSON
CARPENTER	PERSON
c.	O
1996	DATE
The	ORGANIZATION
Boston	ORGANIZATION
Globe	ORGANIZATION
For	O
Carolyn	PERSON
and	PERSON
Dennis	PERSON
Sims	PERSON
of	O
Pittsburgh	LOCATION
,	O
their	O
honeymoon	O
in	O
Tahiti	LOCATION
was	O
a	O
dream	O
that	O
became	O
a	O
nightmare	O
.	O
As	O
their	O
plane	O
landed	O
,	O
dirt	O
and	O
rocks	O
pelted	O
the	O
windows	O
.	O
Flight	O
attendants	O
screamed	O
in	O
French	O
.	O
Luggage	O
careened	O
from	O
overhead	O
bins	O
and	O
water	O
spilled	O
over	O
the	O
wing	O
.	O
Alas	O
,	O
the	O
747	O
had	O
overshot	O
the	O
runway	O
and	O
landed	O
in	O
the	O
Pacific	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
Simses	PERSON
emerged	O
relatively	O
unscathed	O
,	O
but	O
later	O
in	O
their	O
honeymoon	O
had	O
to	O
deal	O
with	O
food	O
poisoning	O
,	O
a	O
flat	O
tire	O
and	O
a	O
broken	O
doorknob	O
.	O
But	O
there	O
is	O
a	O
happy	O
ending	O
:	O
The	O
Simses	PERSON
are	O
grand	O
prize	O
winners	O
in	O
the	O
second	O
annual	O
Honeymoon	O
Disasters	O
contest	O
sponsored	O
by	O
Thrifty	ORGANIZATION
Car	ORGANIZATION
Rental	ORGANIZATION
.	O
They	O
will	O
get	O
a	O
second	O
honeymoon	O
in	O
any	O
city	O
in	O
the	O
contiguous	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
that	O
is	O
accessible	O
by	O
a	O
major	O
airline	O
,	O
including	O
air	O
fare	O
,	O
a	O
hotel	O
for	O
three	O
nights	O
and	O
a	O
four-day	O
car	O
rental	O
-LRB-	O
a	O
Thrifty	ORGANIZATION
car	O
,	O
we	O
presume	O
-RRB-	O
.	O
Other	O
entrants	O
'	O
tales	O
of	O
woe	O
:	O
--	O
Robert	PERSON
Nelson	PERSON
of	O
Tucson	LOCATION
arranged	O
for	O
a	O
honeymoon	O
stay	O
with	O
his	O
bride	O
,	O
Kathy	PERSON
,	O
at	O
the	O
Pink	ORGANIZATION
Cloud	ORGANIZATION
hotel	O
in	O
Honolulu	LOCATION
.	O
It	O
sounded	O
nice	O
,	O
but	O
the	O
Pink	ORGANIZATION
Cloud	ORGANIZATION
is	O
in	O
the	O
city	O
's	O
adult-entertainment	O
district	O
and	O
most	O
of	O
the	O
patrons	O
were	O
nearly	O
naked	O
.	O
--	O
Clint	PERSON
and	PERSON
Karen	PERSON
Harris	PERSON
of	O
Irmo	LOCATION
,	O
S.C.	LOCATION
,	O
took	O
a	O
moonlit	O
walk	O
along	O
the	O
beach	O
in	O
Nassau	LOCATION
--	O
and	O
were	O
attacked	O
by	O
machete-wielding	O
thugs	O
.	O
They	O
were	O
forced	O
to	O
jump	O
off	O
a	O
pier	O
and	O
into	O
the	O
ocean	O
,	O
with	O
Clint	PERSON
suffering	O
a	O
cut	O
arm	O
.	O
Karen	PERSON
created	O
a	O
makeshift	O
tourniquet	O
from	O
her	O
underwear	O
and	O
the	O
couple	O
swam	O
to	O
safety	O
.	O
--	O
Julie	PERSON
Esposito	PERSON
of	O
Ruskin	LOCATION
,	O
Fla.	LOCATION
,	O
discovered	O
in	O
Aruba	LOCATION
that	O
her	O
new	O
swimsuit	O
became	O
invisible	O
when	O
wet	O
.	O
Not	O
to	O
be	O
outdone	O
,	O
her	O
bridegroom	O
,	O
Mike	PERSON
,	O
found	O
that	O
his	O
reversible	O
swim	O
trunks	O
had	O
dyed	O
strategic	O
portions	O
of	O
his	O
anatomy	O
an	O
attractive	O
green	O
--	O
for	O
two	O
weeks	O
!	O
We	O
hope	O
your	O
honeymoon	O
goes	O
smoother	O
.	O
But	O
if	O
it	O
does	O
n't	O
,	O
you	O
,	O
too	O
,	O
can	O
enter	O
Thrifty	ORGANIZATION
's	O
disaster	O
contest	O
.	O
Sad	O
stories	O
must	O
be	O
received	O
by	O
July	DATE
1	DATE
,	O
and	O
the	O
winner	O
will	O
be	O
announced	O
on	O
Valentine	DATE
's	DATE
Day	DATE
1997	DATE
.	O
Write	O
to	O
Honeymoon	O
Disasters	O
1996	DATE
,	O
c\/o	O
Thrifty	ORGANIZATION
Rent-A-Car	ORGANIZATION
System	ORGANIZATION
Inc.	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Corporate	ORGANIZATION
Communications	ORGANIZATION
Dept	ORGANIZATION
.	ORGANIZATION
,	O
CIMS	O
1020	O
,	O
PO	O
Box	O
35250	O
,	O
Tulsa	LOCATION
,	O
OK	LOCATION
74153-0250	O
.	O
Include	O
a	O
self-addressed	O
,	O
stamped	O
envelope	O
.	O
America	LOCATION
's	O
wettest	O
city	O
.	O
This	DATE
week	DATE
,	O
we	O
ask	O
:	O
What	O
is	O
America	LOCATION
's	O
driest	O
city	O
?	O
-LRB-	O
Answer	O
at	O
end	O
of	O
column	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
In	O
a	O
name	O
:	O
There	O
is	O
a	O
used	O
bookstore	O
in	O
Seattle	LOCATION
called	O
``	O
Twice	O
Sold	O
Tales	O
.	O
''	O
Quotable	O
:	O
``	O
Please	O
remain	O
seated	O
until	O
the	O
aircraft	O
has	O
arrived	O
at	O
the	O
gate	O
.	O
We	O
do	O
n't	O
want	O
any	O
passengers	O
arriving	O
at	O
the	O
terminal	O
before	O
the	O
plane	O
.	O
''	O
heard	O
aboard	O
a	O
United	ORGANIZATION
Airlines	ORGANIZATION
aircraft	O
at	O
Chicago	LOCATION
's	O
O'Hare	LOCATION
Airport	LOCATION
and	O
quoted	O
in	O
Travel	O
Weekly	O
.	O
Beer	O
here	O
:	O
Boston	LOCATION
's	O
newest	O
tour	O
will	O
have	O
you	O
hopping	O
.	O
The	O
Old	O
Town	O
Trolley	O
Tour	O
of	O
Boston	LOCATION
Brew	O
Pubs	O
takes	O
participants	O
to	O
three	O
microbrewery-restaurants	O
John	ORGANIZATION
Harvard	ORGANIZATION
's	ORGANIZATION
Brew	ORGANIZATION
House	ORGANIZATION
in	O
Cambridge	LOCATION
and	O
the	O
Commonwealth	ORGANIZATION
Brewery	ORGANIZATION
Co.	ORGANIZATION
and	O
brew	ORGANIZATION
moon	ORGANIZATION
restaurant	ORGANIZATION
&	ORGANIZATION
microbrewery	ORGANIZATION
,	O
both	O
in	O
Boston	LOCATION
to	O
sample	O
flavorful	O
beers	O
and	O
appetizers	O
.	O
The	O
three-hour	O
tour	O
,	O
complete	O
with	O
a	O
lively	O
naration	O
of	O
the	O
history	O
of	O
brewing	O
,	O
costs	O
$	MONEY
38	MONEY
a	O
person	O
,	O
including	O
tax	O
and	O
tips	O
.	O
-LRB-	O
And	O
bring	O
your	O
ID	O
!	O
-RRB-	O
Tours	O
will	O
be	O
offered	O
today	DATE
and	O
March	DATE
3	DATE
at	O
2	TIME
p.m.	TIME
,	O
March	DATE
19	DATE
at	O
6:30	TIME
p.m.	TIME
and	O
April	DATE
6	DATE
and	DATE
27	DATE
at	O
2	TIME
p.m.	TIME
They	O
will	O
then	O
be	O
held	O
weekly	O
through	O
spring	DATE
and	O
summer	DATE
.	O
For	O
tickets	O
or	O
more	O
information	O
,	O
call	O
(617)269-7150	O
.	O
And	O
speaking	O
of	O
pubs	O
:	O
You	O
have	O
a	O
chance	O
to	O
win	O
a	O
pub	O
in	O
Ireland	LOCATION
,	O
if	O
you	O
're	O
a	O
US	LOCATION
resident	O
over	O
21	O
years	O
old	O
.	O
The	O
prize	O
in	O
the	O
third	O
annual	O
Guinness	O
and	O
Harp	O
contest	O
is	O
the	O
Seanachaoi	ORGANIZATION
Pub	ORGANIZATION
in	O
the	O
charming	O
town	O
of	O
Killalole	LOCATION
on	O
the	O
banks	O
of	O
the	O
River	LOCATION
Shannon	LOCATION
.	O
In	O
50	O
words	O
or	O
less	O
,	O
contestants	O
must	O
write	O
a	O
creative	O
finish	O
to	O
the	O
phrase	O
``	O
Guinness	O
is	O
...	O
''	O
Entry	O
forms	O
are	O
available	O
where	O
Guinness	O
and	O
Harp	O
are	O
sold	O
,	O
or	O
you	O
can	O
write	O
your	O
peerless	O
prose	O
on	O
an	O
8	O
1\/2	O
by	O
11	O
piece	O
of	O
paper	O
and	O
mail	O
it	O
to	O
Guinness	ORGANIZATION
``	O
Win	O
Your	O
Own	O
Pub	O
in	O
Ireland	LOCATION
Contest	O
,	O
''	O
PMI	O
Station	O
,	O
PO	O
Box	O
3585	O
,	O
Southbury	LOCATION
,	O
CT	LOCATION
06488-3585	O
.	O
Entries	O
must	O
be	O
received	O
by	O
March	DATE
31	DATE
.	O
For	O
more	O
information	O
,	O
call	O
(800)	O
ITS	O
MY	O
PUB	O
.	O
Backward	O
:	O
The	O
Chicago	LOCATION
River	LOCATION
is	O
the	O
world	O
's	O
only	O
backward	O
river	O
its	O
flow	O
was	O
reversed	O
by	O
the	O
Army	ORGANIZATION
Corps	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Engineers	ORGANIZATION
at	O
the	DATE
turn	DATE
of	DATE
the	DATE
century	DATE
.	O
The	O
river	O
has	O
another	O
distinction	O
:	O
It	O
is	O
dyed	O
green	O
every	O
St.	DATE
Patrick	DATE
's	DATE
Day	DATE
.	O
Freebie	O
:	O
``	O
A	O
Midwinter	DATE
's	O
Tale	O
,	O
''	O
the	O
Kenenth	PERSON
Branagh	PERSON
comedy	O
,	O
may	O
be	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
latest	O
movies	O
filmed	O
in	O
Britain	LOCATION
but	O
it	O
's	O
hardly	O
the	O
only	O
one	O
.	O
For	O
a	O
map	O
of	O
famous	O
British	O
movie	O
locations	O
and	O
a	O
``	O
BritKit	O
''	O
with	O
a	O
lot	O
of	O
information	O
about	O
visiting	O
the	O
isle	O
,	O
call	O
(800)243-2582	O
.	O
Yummm	O
:	O
airline	O
food	O
!	O
Are	O
there	O
people	O
who	O
like	O
airline	O
food	O
so	O
much	O
that	O
they	O
want	O
to	O
re-create	O
it	O
at	O
home	O
?	O
American	ORGANIZATION
Airlines	ORGANIZATION
thinks	O
so	O
:	O
It	O
is	O
making	O
available	O
to	O
passengers	O
an	O
18-page	O
cookbook	O
,	O
``	O
A	O
Taste	O
of	O
Something	O
Special	O
.	O
''	O
AA	ORGANIZATION
,	O
which	O
has	O
a	O
new	O
and	O
fancier	O
business-class	O
service	O
,	O
speaks	O
of	O
``	O
subtle	O
flavors	O
and	O
tantalizing	O
aromas	O
''	O
and	O
``	O
layers	O
of	O
welcome	O
surprises	O
for	O
the	O
palate	O
.	O
''	O
Recipes	O
range	O
from	O
``	O
Peanut	O
Crusted	O
Chicken	O
with	O
Roasted	O
Banana	O
Honey	O
Sauce	O
''	O
to	O
``	O
Ice	O
Cream	O
Sundae	O
.	O
''	O
Creative	O
renting	O
:	O
After	O
Value	ORGANIZATION
Rent-A-Car	ORGANIZATION
announced	O
an	O
option	O
of	O
renting	O
cars	O
by	O
the	O
hour	O
,	O
a	O
Florida	LOCATION
high	O
school	O
principal	O
rented	O
10	O
convertibles	O
for	O
a	O
two-hour	O
parade	O
.	O
Another	O
hourly	O
renter	O
was	O
a	O
young	O
man	O
who	O
wanted	O
to	O
impress	O
a	O
young	O
woman	O
by	O
driving	O
past	O
her	O
office	O
in	O
a	O
luxury	O
car	O
.	O
-LRB-	O
Rentals	O
begin	O
at	O
99	MONEY
cents	MONEY
an	O
hour	O
.	O
For	O
more	O
information	O
,	O
call	O
800-GO-VALUE	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
Today	DATE
's	O
fractured	O
English	O
lesson	O
:	O
Notice	O
in	O
an	O
Istanbul	LOCATION
hotel	O
:	O
``	O
To	O
call	O
room	O
service	O
,	O
please	O
to	O
open	O
door	O
and	O
call	O
ROOM	O
SERVICE	O
.	O
''	O
Did	O
you	O
guess	O
it	O
?	O
Travel	O
Trivia	O
answer	O
:	O
Phoenix	LOCATION
is	O
America	LOCATION
's	O
driest	O
city	O
,	O
with	O
an	O
average	O
annual	O
rainfall	O
of	O
only	O
7.11	O
inches	O
.	O
-LRB-	O
Send	O
comments	O
and	O
questions	O
to	O
Travel	O
Tidbits	O
,	O
Boston	ORGANIZATION
Globe	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Boston	LOCATION
,	O
MA	LOCATION
02107	O
.	O
Send	O
e-mail	O
to	O
carpen	O
-LRB-	O
AT	O
-RRB-	O
nws.globe.com	O
-RRB-	O
NYT	O
-	O
02-27-96	DATE
1512EST	TIME

BC	O
-	O
CUBA	LOCATION
-	O
ASSESS-2NDTAKE-N	O
02-28	DATE
0355	O
BC	O
-	O
CUBA	LOCATION
-	O
ASSESS-2NDTAKE-NYT	O
HAVANA	LOCATION
:	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
.	O
Though	O
officials	O
here	O
,	O
from	O
Castro	PERSON
on	O
down	O
,	O
like	O
to	O
describe	O
American	O
policy	O
as	O
``	O
37	O
years	O
of	O
unrelenting	O
hostility	O
toward	O
the	O
Cuban	O
revolution	O
,	O
''	O
that	O
overstates	O
the	O
case	O
.	O
President	O
Jimmy	PERSON
Carter	PERSON
,	O
for	O
instance	O
,	O
made	O
consistent	O
efforts	O
from	O
1977	DATE
on	O
to	O
reduce	O
tensions	O
between	O
the	O
two	O
countries	O
and	O
to	O
restore	O
some	O
semblance	O
of	O
diplomatic	O
ties	O
.	O
Castro	PERSON
rewarded	O
him	O
in	O
May	DATE
1980	DATE
with	O
the	O
Mariel	O
crisis	O
and	O
125,000	O
Cuban	O
refugees	O
,	O
which	O
Carter	PERSON
's	O
supporters	O
believed	O
were	O
factors	O
in	O
his	O
defeat	O
at	O
the	O
polls	O
that	DATE
November	DATE
.	O
Throughout	O
his	O
long	O
stay	O
in	O
power	O
,	O
in	O
fact	O
,	O
Castro	PERSON
has	O
taken	O
actions	O
that	O
transformed	O
his	O
domestic	O
woes	O
into	O
confrontations	O
with	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
.	O
Faced	O
with	O
discontent	O
about	O
economic	O
and	O
political	O
conditions	O
that	O
exploded	O
into	O
a	O
street	O
protest	O
in	O
1994	DATE
,	O
he	O
manufactured	O
the	O
crisis	O
that	O
eventually	O
forced	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
to	O
end	O
its	O
30-year	O
policy	O
of	O
automatically	O
treating	O
all	O
Cubans	O
leaving	O
the	O
island	O
as	O
political	O
refugees	O
.	O
Cuban	O
officials	O
obviously	O
knew	O
that	O
an	O
attack	O
on	O
American-based	O
civilian	O
aircraft	O
would	O
bring	O
about	O
yet	O
another	O
crisis	O
with	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
.	O
Adm.	O
Eugene	PERSON
Carroll	PERSON
of	O
the	O
Washington	LOCATION
-	O
based	O
Center	ORGANIZATION
for	ORGANIZATION
Defense	ORGANIZATION
Information	ORGANIZATION
recalls	O
a	O
meeting	O
with	O
the	O
Cuban	ORGANIZATION
Armed	ORGANIZATION
Forces	ORGANIZATION
high	O
command	O
earlier	DATE
this	DATE
month	DATE
in	O
which	O
he	O
was	O
asked	O
what	O
would	O
happen	O
if	O
Cuban	O
MIG	O
's	O
shot	O
down	O
one	O
of	O
the	O
exiles	O
'	O
aircraft	O
.	O
``	O
My	O
answer	O
was	O
that	O
it	O
would	O
be	O
a	O
political	O
disaster	O
,	O
the	O
people	O
in	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
who	O
claim	O
we	O
are	O
not	O
being	O
tough	O
enough	O
on	O
Cuba	LOCATION
would	O
seize	O
on	O
it	O
as	O
evidence	O
we	O
have	O
to	O
get	O
tougher	O
,	O
''	O
recalled	O
Carroll	PERSON
,	O
who	O
was	O
leading	O
a	O
delegation	O
of	O
retired	O
American	O
diplomats	O
and	O
soldiers	O
.	O
But	O
the	O
Cuban	O
officers	O
reacted	O
as	O
if	O
they	O
were	O
under	O
siege	O
by	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
,	O
Carroll	PERSON
said	O
,	O
arguing	O
that	O
``	O
moving	O
the	O
headquarters	O
of	O
the	O
Southern	ORGANIZATION
Command	ORGANIZATION
from	O
Panama	LOCATION
to	O
Miami	LOCATION
indicates	O
a	O
greater	O
focus	O
on	O
Cuba	LOCATION
,	O
''	O
and	O
increased	O
the	O
likelihood	O
``	O
we	O
will	O
foment	O
internal	O
disorder	O
,	O
and	O
use	O
that	O
as	O
an	O
excuse	O
to	O
invade	O
.	O
''	O
Overall	O
,	O
Carroll	PERSON
said	O
,	O
the	O
Cuban	O
high	O
command	O
seemed	O
to	O
him	O
to	O
be	O
``	O
paranoid	O
and	O
highly	O
suspicious	O
.	O
''	O
NYT	O
-	O
02-28-96	DATE
2101EST	TIME

BC	O
-	O
NAVY	ORGANIZATION
-	O
CRASHES-SPI	O
&LR;	O
03-01	DATE
BC	O
-	O
NAVY	ORGANIZATION
-	O
CRASHES-SPI	O
UNPRECEDENTED	O
SPATE	O
OF	O
NAVY	ORGANIZATION
CRASHES	O
PUZZLES	O
INVESTIGATORS	O
-LRB-	O
For	O
use	O
by	O
New	ORGANIZATION
York	ORGANIZATION
Times	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
clients	O
.	O
-RRB-	O
By	O
ED	PERSON
OFFLEY	PERSON
c.	O
1996	DATE
Seattle	ORGANIZATION
Post-Intelligencer	ORGANIZATION
Sixteen	O
people	O
have	O
been	O
killed	O
and	O
18	O
aircraft	O
have	O
been	O
destroyed	O
in	O
an	O
extraordinary	O
rash	O
of	O
accidents	O
involving	O
the	O
Pacific	ORGANIZATION
Fleet	ORGANIZATION
naval	O
air	O
force	O
since	O
January	DATE
1995	DATE
,	O
leaving	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
investigators	O
baffled	O
.	O
In	O
the	O
first	DATE
eight	DATE
weeks	DATE
of	DATE
this	DATE
year	DATE
alone	O
,	O
the	O
Pacific	ORGANIZATION
Fleet	ORGANIZATION
's	O
air	O
arm	O
has	O
experienced	O
seven	O
crashes	O
in	O
which	O
12	O
people	O
and	O
eight	O
aircraft	O
have	O
been	O
lost	O
,	O
including	O
last	DATE
Saturday	DATE
's	O
loss	O
of	O
a	O
Whidbey	LOCATION
Island	LOCATION
-	O
based	O
EA-6B	O
Prowler	O
in	O
the	O
waters	O
off	O
Southern	LOCATION
California	LOCATION
,	O
where	O
two	O
of	O
its	O
four	O
crewmen	O
perished	O
.	O
``	O
There	O
is	O
no	O
common	O
thread	O
-LRB-	O
to	O
the	O
accidents	O
-RRB-	O
and	O
that	O
is	O
frustrating	O
everyone	O
,	O
''	O
said	O
one	O
senior	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officer	O
,	O
who	O
asked	O
to	O
remain	O
anonymous	O
.	O
Other	O
officials	O
who	O
have	O
reviewed	O
preliminary	O
evidence	O
agree	O
that	O
even	O
in	O
accidents	O
involving	O
the	O
same	O
aircraft	O
models	O
there	O
is	O
no	O
obvious	O
connection	O
.	O
After	O
Saturday	DATE
's	O
EA-6B	O
crash	O
,	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
,	O
in	O
an	O
unprecedented	O
safety	O
move	O
,	O
grounded	O
an	O
entire	O
carrier	O
air	O
wing	O
indefinitely	O
to	O
review	O
flight	O
safety	O
procedures	O
.	O
The	O
Prowler	O
crash	O
from	O
the	O
USS	O
Kitty	O
Hawk	O
marked	O
the	O
fourth	O
jet	O
from	O
Carrier	ORGANIZATION
Air	ORGANIZATION
Wing	ORGANIZATION
11	ORGANIZATION
,	O
the	O
wing	O
now	O
grounded	O
,	O
to	O
be	O
lost	O
since	O
Jan.	DATE
1	DATE
,	O
and	O
its	O
seventh	O
to	O
crash	O
in	O
the	O
past	DATE
two	DATE
years	DATE
,	O
officials	O
said	O
.	O
Investigators	O
are	O
looking	O
at	O
everything	O
from	O
maintenance	O
problems	O
to	O
adequacy	O
of	O
spare	O
parts	O
and	O
effectiveness	O
of	O
pilot	O
safety	O
training	O
,	O
but	O
report	O
no	O
common	O
clues	O
to	O
the	O
mishaps	O
so	O
far	O
.	O
Meanwhile	O
,	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
have	O
imposed	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
safety	O
``	O
stand	O
down	O
''	O
periods	O
for	O
fliers	O
to	O
review	O
flying	O
safety	O
rules	O
and	O
survival	O
skills	O
,	O
while	O
investigators	O
have	O
pored	O
over	O
accident	O
data	O
to	O
determine	O
why	O
the	O
aircraft	O
went	O
down	O
.	O
Among	O
the	O
problems	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
is	O
dealing	O
with	O
:	O
--	O
The	O
eight	O
aircraft	O
lost	O
this	DATE
year	DATE
constitute	O
nearly	O
40	PERCENT
percent	PERCENT
of	O
the	O
21	O
aircraft	O
losses	O
suffered	O
by	O
the	O
Pacific	ORGANIZATION
Fleet	ORGANIZATION
command	O
in	O
an	O
entire	O
two-year	O
period	O
.	O
Eight	O
military	O
fliers	O
and	O
three	O
civilians	O
were	O
killed	O
.	O
By	O
contrast	O
,	O
the	O
Atlantic	ORGANIZATION
Fleet	ORGANIZATION
's	O
naval	O
air	O
force	O
lost	O
only	O
four	O
aircraft	O
in	O
all	DATE
of	DATE
1995	DATE
and	O
has	O
recorded	O
no	O
aircraft	O
accidents	O
so	O
far	O
this	DATE
year	DATE
,	O
said	O
spokesman	O
Cmdr	O
.	O
Kevin	PERSON
Wensing	PERSON
.	O
--	O
In	O
the	O
past	DATE
16	DATE
months	DATE
,	O
eight	O
Pacific	LOCATION
-	O
based	O
F-14	O
Tomcat	O
fighters	O
have	O
crashed	O
,	O
including	O
three	O
in	O
January	DATE
this	DATE
year	DATE
.	O
During	O
the	O
same	O
interval	O
,	O
only	O
two	O
F-14s	O
based	O
in	O
the	O
Atlantic	LOCATION
region	O
were	O
lost	O
.	O
The	O
accidents	O
,	O
particularly	O
a	O
fiery	O
crash	O
in	O
Nashville	LOCATION
that	O
killed	O
the	O
two	O
aircrewmen	O
and	O
three	O
civilians	O
,	O
prompted	O
officials	O
to	O
relieve	O
the	O
squadron	O
commander	O
involved	O
,	O
to	O
ground	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
's	O
entire	O
F-14	O
fleet	O
for	O
a	O
72-hour	O
safety	O
review	O
,	O
and	O
has	O
prompted	O
a	O
congressional	O
inquiry	O
that	O
will	O
hold	O
hearings	O
in	O
mid-April	DATE
.	O
After	O
the	O
crash	O
last	DATE
Saturday	DATE
,	O
the	O
vice	O
admiral	O
commanding	O
Pacific	LOCATION
naval	O
air	O
forces	O
took	O
the	O
unprecedented	O
step	O
of	O
ordering	O
the	O
entire	O
air	O
wing	O
off	O
the	O
carrier	O
.	O
VAQ	ORGANIZATION
135	ORGANIZATION
's	O
remaining	O
three	O
aircraft	O
and	O
240	O
enlisted	O
personnel	O
returned	O
to	O
Whidbey	LOCATION
Island	LOCATION
Naval	LOCATION
Air	LOCATION
Station	LOCATION
,	O
Wash.	LOCATION
,	O
Sunday	DATE
night	TIME
,	O
said	O
base	O
spokesman	O
Howard	PERSON
Thomas	PERSON
.	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
Wing	ORGANIZATION
11	ORGANIZATION
remains	O
grounded	O
indefinitely	O
,	O
Thomas	PERSON
said	O
.	O
Additionally	O
,	O
all	O
naval	O
aviation	O
units	O
in	O
the	O
Pacific	LOCATION
have	O
been	O
ordered	O
to	O
conduct	O
a	O
safety	O
48-hour	O
``	O
stand	O
down	O
''	O
between	O
now	O
and	O
March	DATE
5	DATE
in	O
which	O
the	O
fliers	O
will	O
undergo	O
a	O
concentrated	O
review	O
of	O
safety	O
procedures	O
.	O
The	O
recent	O
crashes	O
are	O
all	O
under	O
investigation	O
and	O
can	O
not	O
be	O
discussed	O
in	O
detail	O
,	O
said	O
Cmdr	O
.	O
Greg	PERSON
Hartung	PERSON
,	O
spokesman	O
for	O
Pacific	ORGANIZATION
Fleet	ORGANIZATION
naval	O
air	O
forces	O
.	O
The	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
launches	O
two	O
separate	O
investigations	O
when	O
an	O
aircraft	O
crashes	O
.	O
A	O
legal	O
inquest	O
conducted	O
by	O
aviators	O
looks	O
into	O
the	O
incident	O
to	O
determine	O
not	O
only	O
the	O
cause	O
of	O
the	O
crash	O
,	O
but	O
to	O
recommend	O
disciplinary	O
measures	O
if	O
a	O
person	O
is	O
responsible	O
for	O
the	O
accident	O
.	O
A	O
separate	O
safety	O
review	O
is	O
conducted	O
to	O
obtain	O
information	O
used	O
by	O
the	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
Safety	ORGANIZATION
Center	ORGANIZATION
to	O
formulate	O
operating	O
and	O
safety	O
policies	O
.	O
Vice	O
Adm.	O
Brent	PERSON
Bennitt	PERSON
,	O
who	O
has	O
seen	O
seven	O
of	O
his	O
command	O
's	O
aircraft	O
go	O
down	O
since	O
he	O
assumed	O
command	O
of	O
Pacific	ORGANIZATION
Fleet	ORGANIZATION
naval	O
air	O
forces	O
only	O
four	DATE
weeks	DATE
ago	DATE
,	O
said	O
in	O
San	LOCATION
Diego	LOCATION
there	O
seemed	O
to	O
be	O
no	O
common	O
denominator	O
to	O
the	O
crashes	O
,	O
such	O
as	O
poor	O
maintenance	O
or	O
equipment	O
failures	O
.	O
The	O
aircrews	O
are	O
receiving	O
adequate	O
numbers	O
of	O
monthly	O
flight	O
hours	O
,	O
he	O
added	O
.	O
Bennitt	PERSON
said	O
he	O
is	O
concerned	O
that	O
in	O
three	O
of	O
the	O
recent	O
crashes	O
,	O
including	O
the	O
Whidbey	LOCATION
-	O
based	O
Prowler	O
loss	O
,	O
it	O
appeared	O
that	O
the	O
aircrew	O
attempted	O
to	O
eject	O
too	O
late	O
to	O
survive	O
.	O
``	O
There	O
is	O
a	O
point	O
beyond	O
which	O
an	O
aircrew	O
knows	O
that	O
either	O
the	O
airplane	O
is	O
out	O
of	O
control	O
and	O
they	O
have	O
exceeded	O
the	O
limits	O
beyond	O
which	O
they	O
should	O
not	O
stay	O
with	O
the	O
airplane	O
,	O
''	O
Bennitt	PERSON
said	O
,	O
referring	O
to	O
extensive	O
safety	O
and	O
survival	O
training	O
each	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
flier	O
undergoes	O
.	O
All	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
aviators	O
are	O
being	O
given	O
refresher	O
training	O
in	O
ejection	O
and	O
survival	O
skills	O
,	O
officials	O
said	O
.	O
For	O
the	O
F-14	O
fighters	O
,	O
several	O
flight	O
operating	O
restrictions	O
have	O
been	O
imposed	O
to	O
prevent	O
engine	O
stalls	O
,	O
a	O
common	O
problem	O
with	O
the	O
aircraft	O
's	O
underpowered	O
engines	O
,	O
Bennitt	PERSON
noted	O
.	O
In	O
Washington	LOCATION
,	O
D.C.	LOCATION
,	O
the	O
House	ORGANIZATION
National	ORGANIZATION
Security	ORGANIZATION
Committee	ORGANIZATION
plans	O
hearings	O
in	O
April	DATE
that	O
will	O
focus	O
on	O
funding	O
adequacy	O
of	O
aircraft	O
maintenance	O
and	O
spare	O
parts	O
.	O
Meanwhile	O
,	O
naval	O
aviators	O
are	O
gritting	O
their	O
teeth	O
as	O
they	O
wait	O
for	O
the	O
green	O
light	O
to	O
resume	O
training	O
.	O
``	O
No	O
one	O
wanted	O
to	O
come	O
into	O
port	O
,	O
''	O
the	O
senior	O
Navy	ORGANIZATION
official	O
said	O
of	O
Air	ORGANIZATION
Wing	ORGANIZATION
11	ORGANIZATION
following	O
the	O
Whidbey	LOCATION
Prowler	O
crash	O
.	O
``	O
They	O
are	O
ready	O
to	O
go	O
back	O
out	O
and	O
do	O
it	O
again	O
.	O
''	O
NYT	O
-	O
03-01-96	DATE
2040EST	TIME
